<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Miscellanea, or, A choice collection of wise and ingenious sayings, &amp;c of princes, philosophers, statesmen, courtiers, and others out of several antient and modern authors, for the pleasurable entertainment of the nobility and gentry of both sexes / by G.M.</title>
            <author>Miege, Guy, 1644-1718?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 86 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50818</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2014</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31228</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11791827</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11791827</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49233</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50818)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49233)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1488:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Miscellanea, or, A choice collection of wise and ingenious sayings, &amp;c of princes, philosophers, statesmen, courtiers, and others out of several antient and modern authors, for the pleasurable entertainment of the nobility and gentry of both sexes / by G.M.</title>
                  <author>Miege, Guy, 1644-1718?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 163 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Lindsey ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed, March 12, 1693/4, Edward Cooke" on p. [8]</note>
                  <note>Postscript, p. 135-163.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Miege by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49233:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49233:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>MISCELLANEA:</hi> OR, A Choice Collection OF <hi>Wiſe and Ingenious Sayings,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>OF <hi>Princes, Philoſophers, Stateſmen, Courtiers,</hi> and Others; Out of ſeveral Antient and Modern Authors: For the pleaſurable Entertainment of the Nobility and Gentry of both Sexes.</p>
            <p>By <hi>G. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diſperſa Colligo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Lindſey</hi> at the Angel near Lincolns-Inn in <hi>Chancery-Lane,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49233:2"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:49233:2"/>
            <p>TO The Honourable <hi>EDWARD IRBY</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> (Eldeſt Son of ANTHONY, and Grandſon to the Moſt Worthy Knight Sir ANTHONY IRBY, both Deceaſed) The Heir, and greateſt Hopes of his Illuſtrious Family, This MISCELLANY Of <hi>Wiſe and Ingenious Sayings,</hi> &amp;c. Is humbly Dedicated By the Author.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49233:3"/>
            <pb n="v" facs="tcp:49233:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Deſign of this <hi>MIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CELLANY</hi> is, both to Inſtruct and Divert. The Inſtructive Part, conſiſting of <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Ingenious Sayings,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries along with it a great deal of good Hiſtory and Morality. In which Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings the ancient <hi>Greeks,</hi> whilſt Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flouriſhed amongst them, excelled to admiration.</p>
            <p>The Diverting Part (made up of witty <hi>Jeſts,</hi> ſmart <hi>Repartees,</hi> and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant <hi>Fancies,</hi> Intermixt with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and moſt of 'em above the ſtrain of popular Wit) aims at nothing but Innocent Mirth; being free from obſcene and prophane Expreſſions, too frequent in other Works of this kind. Whereby the Age is corrupted in a
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:49233:4"/>
great meaſure, and Youth inflamed to looſe and wanton Thoughts. Whereas this Collection may ſerve to frame their Minds to ſuch Flaſhes of Wit as may be agreeable to civil and genteel Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. The <hi>Epitaphs</hi> I own to be for the moſt part extracted out of <hi>Camb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den's Remains;</hi> but ſo culled and ſifted from the reſt, that you have here the choiceſt only. Some of 'em of a ſerious, and others of a merry ſtrain; ſome <hi>Latin,</hi> and others <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you have here <hi>Honeſtum, Utile, &amp; Jucundum,</hi> uſeful Morality, and witty Diverſion. The whole reduced under proper Heads, not huddled up confuſedly together, as are commonly other Works of this nature.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="vii" facs="tcp:49233:4"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>OF Princes, <hi>Pag. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Popes, <hi>Pag. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cardinals, <hi>Pag. 18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Biſhops, <hi>Pag. 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Stateſmen and Courtiers, <hi>Pag. 26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Magiſtrates, <hi>Pag. 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ladies, <hi>Pag. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Love and Gallantry, <hi>Pag. 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Roman Prieſts, Jeſuits, and Monks, <hi>Pag. 49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lawyers, <hi>Pag. 58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Phyſicians, <hi>Pag. 61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Orators and Philoſophers, <hi>Pag. 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Authors, <hi>Pag. 69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Poets, <hi>Pag. 74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Painters and Pictures, <hi>Pag. 79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Scholars, <hi>Pag. 81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>War, Officers and Souldiers, <hi>Pag. 83</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tradeſmen, and Countrymen, <hi>Pag. 87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Maſters, and Servants, <hi>Pag. 91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Marry'd Men and Women, <hi>Pag. 95</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dying Men and Women, <hi>Pag. 102</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Buryings, <hi>Pag. 107</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Epitaphs, <hi>Pag. 110</hi>
               </item>
               <item>POSTSCRIPT, <hi>Pag. 135</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:49233:5"/>
            <p>LICENSED,</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>March</hi> 12. 1693/4.</date>
               <signed>Edward Cooke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49233:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>MISCELLANEA; OR,</hi> Wiſe and Ingenious Sayings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of PRINCES.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>GREAT was the Freedom the ancient Greeks took with their Princes, even to the Reproach of their Vices; and ſome of theſe were wiſe enough not to take it ill: Witneſs the Story of a Grecian Lady, and <hi>PHILIP</hi> King of <hi>Macedon.</hi> Which King newly riſen from Table, his Head intoxicated with the Liquor he had drunk, wronged the Lady in a Concern ſhe brought before him. Whereupon ſhe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed from his Judgment, <hi>To whom?</hi> ſaid the King; <hi>To Philip,</hi> reply'd ſhe, <hi>when Sober.</hi> This made him Recollect himſelf; and, upon due Conſideration, finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49233:6"/>
in the wrong, he altered his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Lady's behalf.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame King, having ſome Courtiers about him, who endeavoured to perſwade him to puniſh a Man of great Worth, as having ſpoken ill of him, <hi>I muſt firſt exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> (ſays he) <hi>whether I have deſerved it, or not.</hi> At laſt he found, that the Party had never receiv'd any Favour from him, thô he highly deſerved it. Upon which he ſent him great Preſents; and 'twas not long before he heard, that the ſame Man ſpoke much to his Praiſe. <hi>You ſee,</hi> then ſaid the King to the ſame Courtiers, <hi>that I know better than you do how to ſilence De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction.</hi> To which he added, that <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces had it in their Power to get the Love of their Subjects when they pleaſed; and, if they were not beloved, 'twas their own Fault.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PHILIP</hi> contending with an able Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian about an Air, <hi>'Twere great pity</hi> (ſaid the Muſician to him) <hi>that you ſhould be ſo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy as to know this better than I do.</hi> A proper Leſſon for Men in Dignity, not to affect excelling in ſome ſorts of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>King <hi>Philip</hi>'s Wife, Mother of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the Great, hearing that her Son called
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49233:6"/>
himſelf the Son of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped as a God, did put a ſhrewd Jeer upon him, For ſhe ſent him word, and pray'd him, <hi>not to bring her into Trouble with the Goddeſs</hi> Juno.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALEXANDER,</hi> being at <hi>Delphos</hi> to conſult the Oracle, forced <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Prieſteſs into the Temple, upon an unlawful Day. She cry'd out, and made what Reſiſtance ſhe could, but in vain. At laſt ſays ſhe to <hi>Alexander, Thou art Invincible. This Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,</hi> anſwered he, <hi>will ſerve my Turn,</hi> and ſo let her go. Thus the Prieſteſs's Words, extorted by his Violence, paſſed for an Oracle.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Darius,</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> having offered his Daughter, with half his Kingdom, to <hi>ALEXANDER, Parmenio</hi> his Favourite told him, <hi>Were I</hi> Alexander, <hi>I would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of</hi> Darius <hi>his Offer. So would I,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied <hi>Alexander, if I were</hi> Parmenio.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>ALEXANDER</hi> lay dying, ſome of his Courtiers asked him, where he had laid up his Treaſures. <hi>You will find them,</hi> ſays he, <hi>in my Friends Purſes.</hi> Whereby he inſinuated, that he had got no Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, but what he had freely (as faſt as he had got them) diſpoſed of amongſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49233:7"/>
his Friends; and that he did not queſtion but they would ſupply therewith one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when Occaſion ſerved.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>King <hi>ANTIGON<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> having made a ſtrict League with the Athenians, they offered one of his Servants the Freedom of their City. <hi>By no means,</hi> ſaid the King, <hi>I will not ſuffer him to accept of that Honour, leſt that being ſome Day or other in a Paſſion, I ſhould be ſo unhappy as to beat an</hi> Athenian.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>King <hi>PIRRH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> having twice over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Romans, and finding his Army much weakned by ſuch Victories, <hi>I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done,</hi> ſays he, <hi>if I get a third Victory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>X.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> Tyrant of <hi>Syracuſa,</hi> was a Prince who freely ridiculed the Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Idolatry which reigned in his Time amongſt the Greeks. He was for making uſe of thoſe Offerings that were made to the Idols, which they had no Occaſion for. The Cloak of Gold which <hi>Hieron</hi> ſent to the Statue of <hi>Jupiter Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius</hi> he took, and gave inſtead of it one made of Wool, ſaying, That <hi>a Cloak of Gold was both too cold in Winter, and too warm in Summer. Aeſculapius</hi> his Statue had a Beard of Gold, which he clipt off, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That <hi>it was not decent for the Son to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49233:7"/>
have a Beard, being his Father</hi> Apollo <hi>had none.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dionyſius</hi> had a Son, who had violated a Lady of <hi>Syracuſa.</hi> Upon which he ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, with an angry Look, whether he had ever heard that in his Youthful Days he had committed ſuch Actions. <hi>You were not,</hi> anſwered he, <hi>born a King's Son, as I am. Thou ſhalt never be a King's Father,</hi> replied the Tyrant. And ſo it proved in effect. For young <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> being expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from <hi>Syracuſa,</hi> became of a King a Schoolmaſter in the City of <hi>Corinth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Then it was that <hi>Diogenes,</hi> ſeeing him in that Station, began to ſigh before him. Upon which young <hi>Dionyſius</hi> ſpake to him in theſe Words; <hi>Be not troubled,</hi> Diogenes, <hi>at my Misfortunes, 'tis the Fate of humane Affairs. That is not,</hi> anſwered the Cynick, <hi>the Thing which troubles me; for I am vexed, to ſee thee ſtill happier than thou deſerveſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Memorable is <hi>HANNIBAL</hi>'s Anſwer to King <hi>ANTIOCH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi> Who, having ſet forth unto him the Magnificence of his Army, asked him, whether he thought it would be ſufficient for the Romans. <hi>No doubt of it,</hi> anſwered <hi>Hannibal, were the</hi> Romans <hi>never ſo Covetous;</hi> Meaning,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49233:8"/>
that it was ſufficient to make 'em rich with the Spoils, but not to overcome them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis ſaid of <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CAESAR,</hi> that having took Shipping at <hi>Brunduſium</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> in Purſuit of <hi>Pompey,</hi> and a Storm ariſing, which frighted his Pilot from ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Sall, he undauntedly cried out to the Pilot, <hi>Caeſarem vehis &amp; Fortunam ejus,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that thou carrieſt <hi>Caeſar</hi> and his Fortune.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>WILLIAM R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> upon the like Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, ſhewed his greatneſs of Courage much after the ſame manner. Who go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to take Ship for <hi>Normandy,</hi> in order to Relieve <hi>Coutancaes</hi> then ſtraitly beſieged by the French, the Wind then proving contrary and boyſterous, the Mariners told him, it was not ſafe for him to take Sea. But the King eager for the Relief of that Town, and having no Time to loſe, bad them <hi>hoiſe up Sail in God's Name, Was it ever heard</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that a King was drowned by Tempeſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>To this purpoſe was the Anſwer of <hi>CHARLES</hi> V. Emperor, and King of <hi>Spain,</hi> at the Battel of <hi>Tunis.</hi> Who, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing adviſed by the Marqueſs of <hi>Guaſto</hi> to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49233:8"/>
ſecure his Perſon, when the great Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance began to play, <hi>Marqueſs,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>did you ever hear, that an Emperor was ſlain with a great Shot?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CAESAR,</hi> being gone to Conquer <hi>Africk,</hi> hapned to fall off his Horſe. <hi>'Tis a good Omen,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that I find</hi> Africk <hi>under me; This is not a Fall, but Taking of Poſſeſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Much to the ſame purpoſe was that Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an Officer of <hi>WILLIAM</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour, whoſe Foot (upon his Landing in <hi>England</hi>) chanced to ſlip, ſo that he fell into the Mud, and bemired all his hands over. Which Accident being lookt upon by the ſaid Officer as a lucky Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, <hi>Now</hi> (ſaid he to the Duke) <hi>thou haſt taken Poſſeſſion, and holdeſt of the Land in thy band, whereof thou ſhalt be ſhortly King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A young Grecian favoured very much <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S;</hi> who, inquiring into the Cauſe of ſo great Reſemblance, asked the Young Man whether his Mother had ever been at <hi>Rome. No,</hi> anſwered the Young Man, <hi>but my Father has ſeveral times.</hi> Thus, by an apparent Simplicity which ſheltered his Boldneſs from the Emperor's
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49233:9"/>
Anger, he made him ſenſible by his own Argument, that the Reſemblance pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded rather from the Wantonneſs of the Emperor's Mother than his own Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The Trojans having ſent Deputies to Compliment <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> upon account of a Palm-tree that grew on an Altar they had erected unto him, told him, it was a certain Preſage of the Conqueſts he ſhould make. <hi>To me,</hi> anſwered <hi>Auguſtus, 'tis ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Argument how little Fire you Kindle upon the Altar, to conſume the Victims.</hi> Apparet quàm ſaepe accendatis.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Admirable is that ſaying of a wiſe Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, upon the Death of <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S. 'Twere</hi> (ſays he) <hi>to be wiſhed, that either</hi> Auguſtus <hi>had never been born, or that he had never died.</hi> By which few Words he gave a juſt Idea of the whole Life of that Prince. The Beginning of whoſe Reign was full of Violence and Cruelty, whereas the Progreſs and Concluſion of it was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with all the Bleſſings of Juſtice, Clemency, and Moderation.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>When the Trojans ſent Embaſſadors to <hi>TIBERI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> to condole the Death of his Father-in-Law <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> it was ſo long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49233:9"/>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> his Death, that <hi>Tiberius</hi> thought it proper to fit them with this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn. <hi>And I am,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſorry, that you have loſt ſo valiant a Knight as</hi> Hector; who was ſlain above a thouſand Years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>SIGISM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ND</hi> the Emperor, being told by one of his Courtiers, that he wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at his Maxim of obliging his Enemies, and putting them in a Condition to hurt him, when it was in his Power to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their Lives. <hi>Do not I,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſlay 'em, when by my Benefits I make them of my Foes my Friends.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>LEWIS</hi> XII, King of <hi>France,</hi> when he was Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> had been very much diſobliged in the foregoing Reigns by two Perſons then in great Favour at Court. When he came to the Crown, a Confident of his did his utmoſt to induce him into a Reſentment. <hi>By no means,</hi> anſwered King <hi>Lewis, 'tis below a King of</hi> France <hi>to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the Wrong done to the Duke of</hi> Orle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>No leſs memorable is the generous An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of <hi>JOHN</hi> II, Duke of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> who was an Hoſtage in <hi>England</hi> for King <hi>John</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> Whilſt he was here, ſeveral
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49233:10"/>
of his Subjects taking an advantage of his Abſence caballed againſt him, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded his Rights. One of his Officers took an exact Account of it in writing, which he preſented to the Duke upon his Return, in order to bring the Offenders under the Laſh of the Law. The Duke asked him, whether he had took an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the good Service they had done him formerly. That I have not, ſaid the Officer. <hi>Then,</hi> ſaid the Duke, <hi>it is not juſt I ſhould make any <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of this;</hi> and ſo threw it into the Fire, without any further notice.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>HENRY</hi> IV, of <hi>France,</hi> walking one Day, was followed by the Duke of <hi>Mayenne,</hi> a burly fat Man, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently a bad Walker; who had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with <hi>Henry</hi> for the Crown. And now the King took pleaſure in tiring of him. But, after the Walking was over, <hi>Now Couſin</hi> (ſaid the King to him) <hi>I am ſatisfy'd, and you may aſſure your ſelf I ſhall take no further Revenge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>LEWIS</hi> XIII, Son and Succeſſor of the foreſaid <hi>Henry,</hi> being addreſſed unto by a Deputation from his Proteſtant Subjects, for the Continuation of their Privileges, according to the Edicts of his Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49233:10"/>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> III, and <hi>Henry</hi> IV, the King made them this Anſwer. <hi>You had,</hi> ſays he, <hi>thoſe Privileges granted you by</hi> Henry III, <hi>who feared you; and you had them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by my Father, who loved you; but for my Part, I neither love, nor fear you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The late Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> making his firſt Viſit to <hi>LEWIS</hi> XIV, after the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel of <hi>Seneffe,</hi> the King ſtood at the Top of the Stairs, whilſt the Prince was get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up but ſlowly, having the Gout upon him. Which made him ſay to the King from the middle of the Stair-caſe, <hi>Sir, I beg your Majeſty's Pardon, if I make you ſtay. Couſin,</hi> anſwered the King, <hi>take your own Time; a Prince loaded with Laurels, as you are, cannot move ſo nimbly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXIX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A petty PRINCE of <hi>Italy,</hi> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that a Frenchman in his Court had put ſome Jokes upon him and his Deſigns, ordered him to go out of his Dominions in three Days. <hi>'Tis too long a Time,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the French Gentleman, <hi>three quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of an Hour will ſerve to obey him.</hi> By which Anſwer he pleaſantly reflected up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſmall Extent of the Prince's Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49233:11"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A KING of <hi>Spain,</hi> unfortunate in War, having loſt ſeveral Places and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of Conſequence, his Courtiers never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs gave him the Title of <hi>Great.</hi> Which one carping at, <hi>his Greatneſs</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is like that of Ditches, which the more is taken from them, grow the greater.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>After the Battels of <hi>Fleury</hi> and <hi>Staffar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,</hi> a Miniſter of the Emperor at the Court of <hi>Portugal</hi> inſinuating to the KING, that <hi>France</hi> muſt yield at laſt, being ſurrounded with Enemies on all Sides. <hi>Ay, but</hi> (anſwered the King) <hi>ſhe has newly made two vigorous Sallies;</hi> Meaning the aforeſaid Battels, in which the French had the Advantage.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>WILLIAM</hi> the <hi>Conquerour,</hi> having created his Half Brother (Biſhop of <hi>Bayeux</hi>) Earl of <hi>Kent,</hi> ordered him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to be Impriſoned, on ſome juſt Diſpleaſure. For which being quarrelled by the Pope, (the Clergy being then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the Secular Power) he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned this Anſwer, That <hi>he had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Earl of</hi> Kent, <hi>not the Biſhop of</hi> Bayeux.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49233:11"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>WILLIAM R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> the Conquerour's Son and immediate Succeſſor, made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly as it were Portſale of the Spiritual Livings. One Day two Monks out-bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding each other for an Abbey, he asked another of their Company, (whom he ſpy'd ſtanding in a Corner) what he would give to be Abbot? <hi>Not one Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>for I renounced the World and Riches, that I might the more ſincerely ſerve my God.</hi> Which Anſwer did ſo take with the King, notwithſtanding his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, that he judged him moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be made Abbot, and accordingly beſtowed <hi>gratis</hi> the Abbey upon him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philip,</hi> the warlike Biſhop of <hi>Beauvais</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> being taken Priſoner by our King <hi>RICHARD</hi> I, the Pope wrote in his behalf to the King, that he would Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe him as a Churchman, and one of his beloved Sons. The King, to vindicate himſelf, ſent to the Pope the Armour in which the Biſhop was taken, with theſe words ingraven upon it, <hi>Vide an haec ſit Tunica Filii tui,</hi> that is, See whether this be thy Son's Coat, or not; being the Words which <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Children ſpake to him, when they preſented him with the Coat of their Brother <hi>Joſeph.</hi> Which the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49233:12"/>
Pope viewing, ſwore, that it was rather the Coat of a Son of <hi>Mars,</hi> than a Son of the Church, and ſo left him wholly at the King's Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The ſaid King <hi>RICHARD,</hi> being told by one <hi>Fulke,</hi> a Prieſt in great eſteem for his Holineſs, that he kept three Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which if he did not diſmiſs, they would procure him God's Wrath; <hi>How ſo?</hi> ſaid the King, <hi>all the World knows, I never had a Child.</hi> Yea, ſaid the Prieſt, you have three; and their Names are <hi>Pride, Covetouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Lechery.</hi> Well, ſaid the King, you ſhall ſee me preſently diſpoſe of them. <hi>The Knights Templars ſhall have</hi> Pride, <hi>the White Monks</hi> Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, <hi>and the Clergy</hi> Lechery. Thus you have my three Daughters beſtowed amongſt you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49233:12"/>
               <head>POPES.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>AN Abbot leaving <hi>Rome,</hi> unſatisfy'd that he could not ſee the Pope all the while he was there, ſaid, That <hi>the Pope was no more the Viſible Head of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis ſaid of Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> VIII, that he came in like a Fox, reigned like a Lion, and died like a Dog. He came to the Papal Chair in 1295, and held it above ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Years. During which he perſecuted the <hi>Gibelline</hi> Faction, to the utmoſt of his Power. And they run ſo much in his head that, when the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noua</hi> came before him upon Aſh-Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day to receive the Aſhes, according to the Cuſtom of the Roman Church, inſtead of ſaying, <hi>Memento quòd Cinis es, &amp; in Cine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem reverteris,</hi> the Words uſed in that Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony, he miſtook the Point, and told him, <hi>Memento quòd</hi> Gibellinus <hi>es, &amp; cum</hi> Gibellinis <hi>morieris.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49233:13"/>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Diſcourſe being held before a Pope concerning the Plurality of Livings, <hi>For my part</hi> (ſaid the Pope) <hi>I have but one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> VIII, was 79 Years old, when he came to the Papal See, and in three Weeks time he raiſed all his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews. He deſired to know by one of his familiar Friends what the World ſaid of him; who anſwered, that his Diligence in raiſing his Family was all the Talk of the Town. <hi>Oh! Oh!</hi> reply'd he, <hi>ſono vinti-tre hore e mezza,</hi> 'tis half an hour paſt 23, meaning his Time was near expired. Now in <hi>Italy</hi> the Clocks ſtrike 24 Hours, whereas ours go not beyond 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Countryman, who lookt upon the Pope as a God on Earth, pray'd his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that he might have two Crops every Year. <hi>You ſhall have it,</hi> ſaid the Pope, <hi>but then every Year muſt be of Twenty four Months.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Favoriti,</hi> the late Pope's Secretary, read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Holineſs ſome Briefs that he had drawn, and explaining them unto him in Italian, the Pope wept for Joy, ſaying, <hi>Coſa diranno di noi nella Poſterita, quando vederanno coſi bella Latinita noſtra?</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49233:13"/>
That is to ſay, What will Poſterity ſay of us, when they ſee this our elegant La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An Aſtrologer having foretold Pope <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> VIII, that a Comet ſhould appear about the middle of his Reign, the Pope fell ſick, when the Comet appeared. But, whereas he flattered himſelf, by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Prediction, that his Reign was but half ſpent, he unexpectedly died, and ſo ended both his Life and Reign.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> VIII, being wrought upon by the Spaniſh Embaſſador in order to declare againſt <hi>France,</hi> the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, to induce him to it, told him, that <hi>France</hi> was in a ſinking Condition, that it was impoſſible for her to hold out againſt ſo many Powers, and that the King was not able any longer to maintain his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. <hi>'Tis true,</hi> anſwered the Pope, <hi>but he makes 'em ſubſist at the Coſt and Charge of his Neighbours.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49233:14"/>
               <head>CARDINALS.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>THE Cardinal of <hi>Retz,</hi> being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called by the French King, went to throw himſelf at his Majeſty's feet. Who, taking him up by the hand, told his Eminence, that he wondered to ſee him with a hoary Head. <hi>Sir,</hi> reply'd the Cardinal, <hi>Thus it is to fall under Your Majeſty's Diſpleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This great Man,</hi> ſays my Author, <hi>lived like himſelf in great State; in order to which he was fain to borrow, but took great care to pay. Before his laſt Voyage to</hi> Rome, <hi>he ſent for all his Creditors, caſt up his Accounts with them, and told them he had but ſuch a Sum to pay 'em in ſome ſhort Time, and that his Brother then preſent would ſtand Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity for it. To which his Creditors made this civil Return, that, far from being come to ask for their Money, they had ſome at his Service. A Lady amongst the reſt ſtood up and offered him</hi> 5000 <hi>Crowns; which ſhe praid him to accept, to ſupply his Occaſions.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49233:14"/>
The Cardinal, amazed at ſo great Civility, expreſſed his Senſe of it in a moſt decent manner. And turning about to his Hatter,</hi> It grieves me, <hi>ſays he,</hi> that I muſt leave this good Man unpaid, to whom I owe a conſiderable Sum. 'Tis true, <hi>anſwered the Hatter,</hi> that I am put to great Straits; but, that your Eminence may ſee, I will not come ſhort of any of your Creditors in point of Civility and Reſpect to your Perſon, here are three Hats more, which I beg your Eminence to accept of, and carry with you to <hi>Rome. This exceſſive Kindneſs from an ordinary Tradeſman, as it ſurpriſed all the Company, ſo it drew Tears from the Cardinal, with Thanks to Providence for the good Will of all of them towards him. And, after his Death, his Brother did ſo punctually anſwer the Cardinal's juſt Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that none of his Creditors loſt any Thing by him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentleman, who was great with the foreſaid Cardinal, went every where with him, except to Church. Which gave oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to his Eminence to tell him, <hi>he was his Friend,</hi> uſque ad Aras.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An Author having dedicated a Latine Book to Cardinal <hi>Richelieu,</hi> and ſent him a Copy of it; the Cardinal anſwered his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49233:15"/>
Civility in theſe three Words only, <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepi, Legi, Probavi;</hi> that is, I have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed the Book you ſent me, and do Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Varillás</hi> ſpeaking to one of Cardinal <hi>Baronius, Ah! poor</hi> Baronius, ſays he, <hi>with his Twelve great Volumes, it was God's great Mercy, that he did write no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> being told, the Peace he had made was not advantagious to the People, made this Return, <hi>'Tis a young Tree,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that bears no Fruit as yet,</hi> dabit Fructum ſuum in tempore.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Inſtead of ſaying, that a certain Biſhop was made Cardinal, the uſual ſaying was, that he was got into the College of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, it being the firſt College he hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be a Member of.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Biſhop at <hi>Rome</hi> came to acquaint Cardinal <hi>Pole,</hi> that he was going to his Dioceſs for a Month. <hi>I am glad on't,</hi> ſaid the Cardinal, <hi>for your ſake, you will ſuffer ſo much the leſs in Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49233:15"/>
               <head>BISHOPS.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Biſhop being gone to <hi>Rome</hi> to make his Court, in order to be made a Cardinal, the Pope told him one Day, that he was informed of his being a Baſtard. To which he made this Anſwer, <hi>V. S. a fatto tanti altri Cardinali Aſini che potrebbe far un Mulo;</hi> That is to ſay, Your Holineſs has made ſo many Aſſes Cardinals, that you may as well raiſe a Mule to that Dignity.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another being gone to <hi>Rome</hi> for the ſame Purpoſe, came home <hi>re infectâ,</hi> and brought a great Cold with him. Which one attributed to his <hi>Coming home without a Cardinal's Cap.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A French Biſhop being conſecrated in the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> in the preſence of a great many Biſhops, making a Semicircle in the <hi>Dome,</hi> a Lady raviſhed with the ſight of them in ſuch Order ſaid, that ſhe thought
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49233:16"/>
her ſelf in Paradiſe. <hi>In Paradiſe,</hi> reply'd a Gentleman who ſtood by her, <hi>there are not ſo many Biſhops of our Church to be ſeen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Gaſcoon,</hi> bearing a Grudge againſt the Biſhop of <hi>Bazas</hi> his Dioceſan, ſwore a great Oath, he would never ſay Prayers any more in his Dioceſs. Croſſing over a River, the Boat had a Miſchance, which made it leak. The Waterman, ſeeing his Boat ſinking, warned the <hi>Gaſcoon</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his Soul to God. <hi>Ay but,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>are we ſtill in the</hi> Bazadois? meaning the foreſaid Biſhop's Dioceſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon ones ſaying, that a certain Biſhop had the Gout; another that ſtood by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the Canon that ſays, <hi>Si quis dixerit Epiſcopum podagrâ laborare, Anathema ſit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Grace</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> having preached a Sermon upon Grace, <hi>I have heard</hi> (ſaid the Biſhop of <hi>Bellay,</hi> one of his Hearers) <hi>a Sermon upon Grace, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with a good grace, by the Biſhop of</hi> Grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Some Country Biſhops, being with the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> told him, they were amazed at one Thing in his Conduct,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49233:16"/>
that he never had any Difference with his Chapter. <hi>'Tis my Opinion,</hi> anſwered the Arch-Biſhop, <hi>that none but Country-Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands will fall a cudgelling their Wives.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame Arch-Biſhop being made Duke and Peer of <hi>France, Now</hi> (ſaid one) <hi>it cannot be ſaid that</hi> Paris <hi>is Peer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Biſhop being often out when he preached, and a Lady hapning to ſee his Picture ſomewhere, <hi>One would think</hi> (ſays ſhe) <hi>that he preaches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>X.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Biſhop of <hi>Grenoble</hi> in <hi>Dauphiné,</hi> who uſed to wear a long Beard, had ſomething faln upon it, as he was eating. Which a Servant of his taking notice of, told him, ſomething did ſtick to his Greatneſſes Beard. <hi>Why not rather,</hi> ſaid one that ſat by, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Greatneſs of your Beard?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another French Biſhop, of great Worth, but a profeſſed Enemy to Monks, had ſome Difference with a great Cardinal, who then governed the Kingdom of <hi>France.</hi> This Cardinal however had him in ſo great eſteem, that he reſolved to draw him into his Party, in order to which he offered him an Abbey. Which the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49233:17"/>
refuſed, ſaying, that his Conſcience would not allow of Plurality of Livings. The Cardinal, amazed at ſo unuſual a Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cety of Conſcience amongſt Clergymen, made him this Return. <hi>My Lord,</hi> ſays he, <hi>you are a good Man; and I would Canonize you for a Saint, if you had not writ (as you have) againſt the Monks. Would to God,</hi> reply'd the Biſhop, <hi>that it were in your Power, and that I deſerved it, then we ſhould be both ſatisfy'd.</hi> Thus he ingeniouſly checkt the Cardinal's Ambition, by tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, that, if he Canonized him, they ſhould be both ſatisfy'd. For then the Cardinal muſt be Pope, and he a Saint, which was the Thing they aimed at.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Biſhop, intertaining ſeveral Prelates at Dinner, made a great ſhew of his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Quantity of Gold and Silver Plate, made by the beſt Workmen that could be got. The Magnificence whereof being admired by the Company, <hi>This I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed,</hi> ſaid the Biſhop, <hi>in order to aſſist the Poor of my Dioceſs.</hi> To which one of the Company anſwered ingeniouſly, <hi>My Lord, you might have ſpared them the Charge of the Making.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Biſhop, in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII, being appointed by the King to go to King
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49233:17"/>
                  <hi>Francis</hi> I, with the Character of Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, in a dangerous Juncture, he repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the King, that ſuch a threatning Embaſſy as he charged him with to ſo high-ſpirited a Prince as <hi>Francis</hi> I, would go near to coſt him his Life, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore begg'd of the King, he would be pleaſed to diſpenſe him with that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. <hi>Fear nothing,</hi> ſaid the King to him, <hi>if the French King were ſo bold as to take away your Life, I ſhould infallibly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge your Death, by taking off many Heads for one from the French now in my Power. I am apt to believe it,</hi> reply'd the Biſhop, ſmiling, <hi>but of all thoſe many Heads there is none ſo fit for my Shoulders as this Head of mine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49233:18"/>
               <head>STATESMEN, <hi>AND</hi> CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RTIERS.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>NOLI videri ſapiens coram Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipe,</hi> is a Leſſon of wiſe <hi>Solomon,</hi> which puts me in mind of a Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugueze Stateſman. Whoſe Prince, the King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> being about to ſend to the Pope, commanded him to write a Letter, whilſt he wrote another, in order to ſend that which he ſhould like beſt of the two. The Lot fell to the Stateſman's Letter, as the beſt penned. Who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fled into <hi>Spain,</hi> thinking himſelf not ſafe in <hi>Portugal,</hi> upon the King's Opinion, that he had outdone him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>When the Wars in Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Time were hot between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> there were Commiſſioners on both Sides appointed to Treat of Peace. Dr. <hi>Dale,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:49233:18"/>
a Maſter of Requeſts, was one named by the Queen for that purpoſe, and the Place of Congreſs a Town of the French <hi>King's.</hi> Where the Commiſſioners on both Sides being met, it was firſt debated in what Tongue the Negotiation ſhould be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. One of the Spaniſh Commiſſioners thinking to give ours a ſhrewd Gird, propoſed the French Tongue (wherein they were beſt skilled) as moſt fit. And for theſe Gentlemen of <hi>England,</hi> I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe (ſays he) they cannot be Ignorant of the Language of their Fellow-Subjects, their Queen being Queen of <hi>France,</hi> as well as of <hi>England. Nay in faith, my Maſters,</hi> (replied Dr. <hi>Dale) the</hi> French <hi>Tongue is too vulgar for a Buſineſs of this Secrecy and Importance, eſpecially in a French Town. We will therefore rather treat in</hi> Hebrew, <hi>the Language of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>whereof your Maſter is King; and I ſuppoſe you are therein as well skilled, as we in the</hi> French <hi>Tongue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Perſon of Quality going upon an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſy, had this particular Inſtruction from his Prince, that his Conduct ſhould be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly oppoſite to that of his Predeceſſor. To which he anſwered, <hi>Sir, I ſhall ſo car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry my ſelf, that your Majeſty ſhan't need to give the like Inſtruction to any one that ſhall ſucceed me.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49233:19"/>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur de Louvois</hi> being ready to ſet out in order to a Campagne, and offering to tell what Place he was going for, <hi>Don't tell us,</hi> ſays <hi>Monſieur de Roquelaure, where you go, for we ſhall give no Credit to it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Lady ſpeaking to a prime Miniſter of State about an Affair of Conſequence, and having no Anſwer from him, <hi>Pray, my Lord,</hi> ſaid ſhe unto him, <hi>ſhew me ſome Sign that you underſtand me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>To a learned Man one may ſay, <hi>Scire tuum Nihil eſt, niſi te ſcire hoc ſciat alter;</hi> thy Knowledg ſignifies nothing, unleſs it be known to the World. To a Stateſman, on the contrary, one muſt ſay, <hi>Si ſciat hoc alter, ſcire tuum nihil eſt,</hi> thy Knowledg avails nothing, unleſs it be private to thy ſelf. For the main part of his Learning is to know, how to keep Counſel.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Miniſter of the Emperor, reſiding before the War at the Court of <hi>France,</hi> walked one day with ſeveral Courtiers in the Gallery of <hi>Verſailles.</hi> Viewing ſome Pictures there, that ſet forth the greateſt Actions of the King, <hi>We have alſo</hi> (ſays he) <hi>wherewithal to ſet out a great Gallery, by the Emperor's Conqueſts. 'Tis true,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49233:19"/>
a Courtier, <hi>and the Duke of</hi> Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain <hi>will have a great Share therein.</hi> By which Anſwer he meant to inſinuate, that, whereas the glorious Actions of King <hi>Lewis</hi> were performed by himſelf, or at leaſt in his Preſence, thoſe of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror were only performed by his Proxy the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and in the Emperor's Abſence.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An old French Courtier, being grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly afflicted with the Gout, received a Viſit of a Prince of the Royal Blood, of whoſe Party he had formerly been. <hi>That which grieves me moſt of all</hi> (ſays he to the Prince) <hi>in the Condition I am in, is, that I have quitted your Service. You ought not to grieve for that,</hi> anſwered the Prince, <hi>now you have the Honour to belong to the King. 'Tis true,</hi> replied the Courtier, <hi>but had I not quitted your Service, I had been long ſince free from the Pain I now ſuffer.</hi> Thus he cunningly taxed the Prince with forſak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Friends, after he had involved them in a Rebellion, for which they had been executed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Venetian Embaſſador going to the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> paſſed through <hi>Florence,</hi> where he went to pay his Reſpects to the late Duke of <hi>Tuſcany.</hi> The Duke com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49233:20"/>
to him of the Embaſſador the State of <hi>Venice</hi> had ſent him, as a Man unworthy of his Character; <hi>Your Highneſs,</hi> ſays he, <hi>muſt not wonder at it, for we have many idle Pates at</hi> Venice. <hi>So we have,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the Duke, <hi>in</hi> Florence, <hi>but we don't ſend them abroad to treat of publick Affairs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>X.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Prince, jeering one of his Courtiers whom he had employ'd in ſeveral Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, told him he looked like an Ox. <hi>I know not,</hi> anſwered he, <hi>whom I am like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; but this I know, that I have had the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſeveral times to Repreſent your Perſon.</hi> A free and pleaſant Repartee, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired a great Familiarity betwixt the Subject and the Prince to be free from Cenſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Roman, having entertained at Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>Mecenas, Auguſtus</hi> his Favourite, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenas</hi> fell entertaining of his Wife with amorous Careſſes, whilſt her Husband made as if he had been aſleep, to give him the more liberty. In the mean time ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of his Slaves, who was ſtealing of a golden Cup, <hi>Thou Rogue</hi> (ſays he) <hi>doſt not thou ſee that I ſleep only for</hi> Mecenas?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A French Courtier, admired for his courtly Carriage, but eſpecially for his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49233:20"/>
Art in reviving a drooping Converſation, ſeeing one day the Court-Ladies ſtand mute before the Queen, amongſt which was <hi>Madame de Guimené,</hi> broke ſilence, and addreſſing himſelf to the Queen, <hi>Is not this, Madam,</hi> ſays he, <hi>an odd Thing in Nature, that</hi> Madame de Guimené <hi>and I being born on the ſame Day, and at no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtance of Time than a quarter of an hour, yet ſhe ſhould be ſo fair, and I ſo black?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> being in a hot Summer day in the Garden of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> between two Pavilions, where the Reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sun made the Heat exceſſive, one of his Attendants took upon him to tell his R. H. that Princes loved no Body. <hi>That can't be apply'd to me,</hi> ſaid the Duke, <hi>who love my Friends very well. If Your Higneſs,</hi> ſaid another, <hi>do's not love 'em boyled, you love 'em however well roſted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Dauphin,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Conty,</hi> and the young Admiral of <hi>France</hi> the Count of <hi>Vermandois,</hi> with ſeveral other Perſons of great Quality, walking one Day along the Canal of <hi>Verſailles,</hi> one came to the young Admiral. And there being upon the Canal a Boat within reach, <hi>Now, my Lord Admiral,</hi> ſays he, <hi>take upon you the Command of this Veſſel, and make a Trial of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49233:21"/>
Skill.</hi> But, whilſt he excuſed himſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Want of Experience, a Gentleman ſtepping amongſt them brought off the Admiral, ſaying, That <hi>he was not a freſh-Water Admiral.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> IV of <hi>France</hi> being come to <hi>Rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en,</hi> a Preſident who came to harang him, fell ſhort of his Speech, and could not conclude it. A Courtier near the King's Perſon told His Majeſty, <hi>Sir, 'tis no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for the</hi> Normans <hi>are mighty apt to fall ſhort of their Word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame King going into a Lady's Chamber, one of his Courtiers hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf under the Bed. A Collation being brought in ſoon after, the King threw a Box full of Sweet-meats under the Bed, ſaying, <hi>Every body muſt live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A French Marqueſs uſed to brag every where, that he had writ to the Queen. Another, who met him by chance in the Palace, cry'd out to him, <hi>Sir, I beg the favour of you to Remember me to the Queen, next time you write to Her Majeſty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A great Officer in the French King's Court, ſhewing his noble Terraſs to the Prince of <hi>Guimené,</hi> told him it ſtood him
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49233:21"/>
but in 25000 Livers. The Prince, who well knew how he came by the Money, made this ſmart Repartee, <hi>I thought,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the King had paid for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A great Bell being made uſe of at a Nobleman's Houſe to ring to Dinner, a Courtier who was to dine with him ſaid, <hi>Will the Dinner anſwer to the Bell?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An Italian being at Dinner with a Court-Officer, who had ſpent all his Eſtate, and ſold a Lordſhip he had, minded how little he did eat, <hi>Your Lordſhip</hi> (ſays he) <hi>do's not eat. No,</hi> anſwered the prodigal Courtier, <hi>for 'tis all eaten.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Something to that purpoſe are theſe French Verſes, made upon one by <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Furetiere;</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Paul vend ſa Maiſon de S. Clou,</l>
                     <l>A maints Creanciers engagée.</l>
                     <l>Il dit par tout, qu'il en eſt ſoû;</l>
                     <l>Je le croi, car il l'a mangée.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A French Courtier, who made it his Buſineſs to be conſtantly at Court, and to appear in the King's Preſence, to relate afterwards in Company what he heard the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49233:22"/>
King ſay, telling one day an old Courtier, that he had ſuch an Account the Night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from the King's Mouth. <hi>And I,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the old Courtier, <hi>heard yeſterday Father</hi> Bourdaloues <hi>Sermon, who preached to me the fineſt Things that ever I heard.</hi> By which Anſwer he ſhewed him the Vanity of his Oſtentation, in appropriating to himſelf alone what the King had ſaid to many more that heard him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>In the late French King's Reign there was a Preſident called <hi>Gouſſaut,</hi> well known for his weak Parts. A Courtier playing at Picket in a publick Place, and finding he had committed an Errour, <hi>I am</hi> (ſays he) <hi>a meer</hi> Gouſſaut. The Preſident, who chanced to be there un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to the Courtier, told him, that he was a Sot. <hi>You ſay right,</hi> replied the Courtier, <hi>that's it I meant to ſay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another, intertaining ſeveral Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men at Dinner, had but one Page to wait at Table. Growing warm with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and deſiring them to be merry, and drink chearfully, <hi>Then</hi> (ſaid one of them) <hi>give us Change for your Page;</hi> Meaning, that he muſt change his Page into Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to ſerve 'em with Wine, as a piece of Gold is changed for ſeveral Pieces of leſs Value.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:49233:22"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Foreign Lord dancing at a Ball in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> did it ſo ungainly, that he made himſelf a laughing-Stock. A Friend of his, to excuſe the Matter, ſaid, <hi>He fights well, though he dances ill. Then let him Fight, and not Dance,</hi> ſaid one who laughed with the reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another being robbed, going over the <hi>Pont-neuf,</hi> and relating the Circumſtances of it, <hi>I don't care</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ſo much for the Loſs of my Money, as for that of ſome Love-Letters I had received from my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris, which the Rogues took along with it. 'Tis ten to one,</hi> anſwered one of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, <hi>but they will find out whoſe Hand it was.</hi> Whereby he inſinuated, as if he had Pick-pockets for his Rivals.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Citizen telling a Courtier, that he had juſt then eaſed himſelf of a great Burden by paying a Debt he owed, and that he could not apprehend how any Man could ſleep that was in Debt; <hi>For my part,</hi> anſwered the Courtier, <hi>I ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wonder how my Creditors can ſleep, well knowing that I ſhall never pay 'em.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another Courtier, being a Confident of the Amours of <hi>Henry</hi> IV of <hi>France,</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49233:23"/>
a Grant from the King, for the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch whereof he apply'd himſelf to the Lord High Chancellor. Who finding ſome Obſtacle in it, the Courtier ſtill inſiſted upon the Grant, and would not allow of any Impediment. <hi>Que chacun ſe mêle de ſon Metier,</hi> ſaid the Chancellour to him, that is, let every one meddle with his own Buſineſs. The Courtier thinking, that he reflected upon him for his Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, <hi>My Imployment</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>is ſuch, that, if the King were but twenty Years youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, I would not change it for three of yours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXIX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Marqueſs, having got out of the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtille,</hi> where he had been impriſoned for a ſlight Offence, came to Court, and did his utmoſt to be taken notice of by the King. Who, being conſcious that he had been too ſevere upon him, had ſome check upon him for it, inſomuch that His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty did not care to look upon him. The Marqueſs perceiving it, made his Addreſs to a Duke, and prayed him to inform the King, that <hi>he freely forgave him, and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of his Majeſty that he would be pleaſed afterwards to look upon him.</hi> The Duke told the King, who being pleaſed with it, ſhewed ever ſince a gracious Countenance to the Marqueſs.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:49233:23"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An envious Courtier being one day ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry melancholy, a Gentleman ask'd what Misfortune had befaln him? <hi>None at all,</hi> anſwered another, <hi>but that the King has preferred a Man of great Worth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A rich Partiſan of <hi>France,</hi> who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly had been a Lackey, going faſt in his Coach through the Streets of <hi>Paris,</hi> a Lady walking by was beſpattered with Dirt by his Horſes. <hi>This Man</hi> (ſays ſhe, ſpeaking of the Partiſan) <hi>is of a revenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Spirit, he dirties us, becauſe we have dir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame Lady went to Law with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Partiſan, who had alſo been a Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key; and being gone to wait upon a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, who was to be a Judg in the Caſe, ſhe ſtaid ſome time with her Livery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in his Withdrawing Room, till he came out of his Chamber. When he came out, he wondered to ſee a Lady of her Quality with none but her Footmen; and was very angry with his Servants, for want of their Information. <hi>A ſhame,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to leave here a Lady of your Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity with none but Lackeys about you. Pray, Sir,</hi> reply'd the Lady, <hi>be not concerned at
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49233:24"/>
it, I am very well pleaſed with my Lackeys, and like them beſt whilſt they keep in that Station.</hi> Thus ſhe cunningly reflected up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her adverſe Party.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> asking a Favour of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter,</hi> ſaid the Queen, <hi>When d'ye mean to leave off Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging? When your Gracious Majeſty,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd he, <hi>leaves off Giving.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:49233:24"/>
               <head>MAGISTRATES.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>CAius Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Bibulus</hi> were Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls of <hi>Rome</hi> together. But this <hi>Bibulus</hi> had done ſo little for the Common-wealth, that when this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulſhip was quoted, becauſe two Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls muſt be named, the Saying was, <hi>In the Conſulſhip of</hi> Caius <hi>and</hi> Caeſar, not of <hi>Caius Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Bibulus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>So ambitious were the Romans of the Conſulſhip, that when <hi>Maximus</hi> died on the laſt Day of his, <hi>Caninius</hi> petition'd, that he might fill up as Conſul the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining part of that Day. Upon which <hi>Tully</hi> made this witty Jeſt, <hi>O vigilantem Conſulem, qui toto Conſulatus ſui tempore ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Oculos non vidit!</hi> O watchful Conſul, who did not ſhut his Eyes all the time of his Conſulſhip!</p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cato</hi> the Cenſor being asked, how it came to paſs, that he had no Statue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in his Honour, who had ſo well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49233:25"/>
of the Common-wealth? <hi>I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> (ſays he) <hi>have this Queſtion asked me, than why I had one erected.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fabricius,</hi> a Roman Conſul, upon the Offer made to him by King <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> his Phyſician, to get him poiſoned, ſent him back his Phyſician with theſe words, <hi>Learn, O thou King, to make a better Choice both of thy Friends and Foes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clodius</hi> being to be tried for his Life by Roman Judges, whom he had bribed with Money to get him off, they deſired a Guard to ſecure them, ſo that the Trial might be free and undiſturbed. But <hi>Clodius</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing acquitted, one <hi>Catulus</hi> made this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion upon them. <hi>What made you,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſo eager for a Convoy? Were you afraid to be robbed of the Money you had of</hi> Clodius?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>After the Reduction of <hi>Paris</hi> to <hi>Henry</hi> IV, a Mareſchal of <hi>France</hi> formerly againſt the King, was bribed into a Submiſſion to him. The Provoſt of Merchants of that City having newly made his Submiſſion in the Name of the City, the ſaid Mareſchal told him, that we ought to render unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the Things that are <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s. <hi>My Lord,</hi> ſaid the Provoſt, <hi>we muſt render it, not ſell it,</hi> reflecting upon the Mareſchal,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49233:25"/>
as a Man bought off out of Rebellion into his Allegiance.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>No leſs Ingenious was the Anſwer of a Lord Mayor to our King <hi>James</hi> I. Who being diſpleaſed with the City, for refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to lend him a Sum of Money he requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, threatned that he would remove his Court, with all the Records of the <hi>Tower,</hi> and the Courts of Judicature, to another Place, with farther Expreſſions of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation. <hi>Your Majeſty,</hi> anſwered the Lord Mayor calmly, <hi>may do what you pleaſe therein, and your City of</hi> London <hi>will ſtill prove dutiful; but ſhe comforts her ſelf with the Thoughts that Your Majeſty will leave the</hi> Thames <hi>behind you.</hi> Whereby he gave the King to underſtand, that as long as the <hi>Thames</hi> ſhould run before the City of <hi>London,</hi> it could not fail of flouriſhing by the Advantage of Trade, whatever Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantages it lay under on his Majeſty's Side.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Witty, but perhaps too Jocoſe for his Circumſtances, was the Anſwer of Sir <hi>Thomas Moor</hi> Lord Chancellor in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. Who, being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the <hi>Tower</hi> by the King, would not ſuffer his Hair or Beard to be cut. And being asked the Reaſon of it, <hi>The
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49233:26"/>
King and I,</hi> ſays he, <hi>are at Law about my Head, and I will be at no Charge to ſet it off, till I know at whoſe Diſpoſal it muſt be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord <hi>Bacon,</hi> before his great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, received a Viſit from Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in a Country-houſe lately built by him. <hi>What made you,</hi> ſaid the Queen to him, <hi>build your Houſe ſo little? Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> anſwered he to the Queen, <hi>I do not build it too little, but 'tis Your Majeſty that made me too great for my Houſe.</hi> An in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Anſwer, expreſſing in few Words both his Modeſty and Gratitude.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>X.</label>
               </p>
               <p>When the Doge of <hi>Genoua</hi> came not long ſince in Perſon to the French Court, with Submiſſions from the Republick lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſutable to a Sovereign State, being at <hi>Verſailles,</hi> and viewing the Magnificence thereof, he was asked by one of the Court, What he thought in it moſt worthy his Admiration? <hi>To ſee my ſelf here,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the Doge very pat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:49233:26"/>
               <head>LADIES.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Lady uſed conſtantly to wait upon another at the beginning of every Year, <hi>to know what Age they muſt go for that Year.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Lady of wonderful Beauty telling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, It was a wonder to ſee her, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this handſom Return, <hi>And when I ſee you, Madam, I may ſay I ſee a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>One that had a Petticoat extravagantly dawbed with Gold and Silver, was wittily asked, <hi>What Goldſmith had made her Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>It was the way of the late Q. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> of <hi>Sweden</hi> to appear always in a Juſtaucor and a Wig. When ſhe came to <hi>Fontaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleau,</hi> a Country Palace of the French King, ſeveral Court-Ladies come to wait on Her Majeſty, ſtept to ſalute her with a Kiſs. The Queen, not liking of it, dropt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49233:27"/>
theſe words, <hi>What Paſſion tranſports theſe Ladies to kiſs me thus? Is it becauſe I look like a young Man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Grandee of <hi>Spain</hi> having a Collar on of the Order of the Golden Fleece, (which the Prince's Favour, not his own Merit, had procured) took particular Notice of a ſparkling Diamond a Court-Lady wore upon one of her Fingers, and ſaid he had rather have the Ring than the Lady. But ſhe fitted him as well. For, having over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard it, ſhe preſently made this Return upon him, <hi>And I ſhould rather chuſe the Halter than the Horſe,</hi> meaning him by the Horſe, and by the Halter his Collar.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An Author holding a fair Lady with both his hands, ſhe got it off from 'em. Upon which a Gentleman that ſtood by told him, <hi>Sir, 'tis the fineſt Piece of Work that ever came out of your hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentleman leading a Lady by the hand, ſhe told him, he held her too faſt. <hi>Madam,</hi> reply'd he, <hi>I'le lay with your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhip that before we part, you will hold me as faſt.</hi> She laid to the contrary. And, whilſt they were ſtepping into a Room, the Gentleman made as if his foot ſlipt; which made her hold him faſt by the hand,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49233:27"/>
to keep him from falling. And then ſhe owned that ſhe loſt the Wager.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Lady, in company with a Gentleman, fell diſcourſing about the Influences of the Month of <hi>May,</hi> when not only the Earth, but all Creatures living upon it, find themſelves revived by the Sun's Heat. After a pretty long Diſcourſe on this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>I dare truſt my Honeſty,</hi> ſaid ſhe to the Gentleman, <hi>all other Months of the Year, which I dare not in</hi> May.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The Place of a Maid of Honour, ſaid one, is very Tickliſh, and difficult to keep.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>X.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Curtizan of <hi>Rome</hi> took place in a Church near a vertuous Lady; Who no ſooner knew her, but ſhe removed to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place. The Curtizan obſerving it, <hi>Why ſhould you, Madam, remove thus for my ſake?</hi> ſaid ſhe to the Lady, <hi>my Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity never proves catching but to ſuch as deſire it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Spaniſh Lady reading in a French Romance a long Converſation betwixt two Lovers, <hi>What a deal of Wit</hi> (ſays the Lady) <hi>is here ill beſtowed? They were toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and they were alone.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:49233:28"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A French Lady of great Wit jeering a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in a Company where a Friend of this Lady was, her Friend took her part, and made the beſt of her. But the firſt took her up, and told her, <hi>I find, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, that you have eaten Garlick.</hi> Now 'tis well known, that thoſe who have eaten Garlick, are not ſenſible of the ill ſmell of others that have alſo eaten of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Court-Lady gone to ſee <hi>Verſailles</hi> in the King's Abſence, <hi>Is not this,</hi> ſaid one to her, <hi>an Inchanted Pallace? 'Tis ſo,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>but it wants the Inchanter,</hi> meaning the King.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An ancient Lady going to viſit a great Man at the point of Death, his Daughter refuſed to let her into his Chamber, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that her Father was not fit for Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Viſits. <hi>Madam,</hi> anſwered the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>there is no Diſtinction of Sex at my Age.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:49233:28"/>
               <head>Of Love, and Gallantry.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gallant, taking his Leave of his dear Miſtris, upon a Journey he could not diſpenſe with, they par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with much ado, and with great Relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctancy. At laſt ſhe told him, <hi>Pray, make all the haſte you can, and remember that a Miſtris is a Benefice that requires Reſidence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis the Way in <hi>Savoy,</hi> the firſt time one has his Vein breathed, to be preſented by his Friends. A Young Man of that Country, having received a Preſent from his Miſtris upon ſuch an Occaſion, returned her Thanks for it, with theſe Words, <hi>You have</hi> (ſays he) <hi>conſidered the Wound of my Arm, but you forget that of my Heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentlewoman who had two Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, one of 'em with a wooden Leg, grew big with Child, and the Queſtion was which of them ſhould father it. He that had the wooden Leg offered to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide it thus. <hi>If the Child,</hi> ſays he, <hi>comes into the World with a wooden Leg, I ſhall father it; if not, the Child ſhall be yours.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:49233:29"/>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A wanton French Gentlewoman, being ordered by the Queen Mother (then Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent) to go into a Monaſtery, he that brought her the Queen's Order, told her, the Queen left her the Liberty to chuſe what Monaſtery ſhe pleaſed. <hi>Then,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>I won't go to a Nunnery, but to a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery of Monks,</hi> which ſhe named, and where ſhe might have Work enough.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another young Lady was to be ſent to a Nunnery of <hi>Filles Repenties,</hi> or Converted Maidens. But a Lady oppoſed it; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked the Reaſon, <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſays ſhe) <hi>ſhe is neither</hi> Converted, <hi>nor</hi> Maiden.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another as wanton as the former, blam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Brother's extravagant Paſſion for Gaming, <hi>When will you leave off Gaming?</hi> ſaid ſhe to him. <hi>When you ceaſe to Love, then I ſhall ceaſe to Play,</hi> anſwered he. <hi>Then,</hi> reply'd the Siſter, <hi>you are like to be a Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter as long as you live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Coldneſs having continued ſome time betwixt two Perſons that formerly had a Love for each other, they met accidentally in a Place, where they fell to play. <hi>But,</hi> ſaid the Gentleman, <hi>What is it we play for? For a Return of Love,</hi> ſaid the Lady.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:49233:29"/>
               <head>Of Roman Prieſts, Jeſuits, and Monks; with Paſſages upon their Preaching, and the Auricular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Roman Prieſt, being grievouſly troubled with the Stone, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be Cut. But, when the Surgeon was ready for the Operation, <hi>Won't it</hi> (ſays he) <hi>diſable me from the Act of Generation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another being in drink, when a Child was brought him to Church to be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, could not find out the Miniſtration of Baptiſm in the Ritual. At laſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving turned over many a Leaf to little purpoſe, <hi>This Child,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is very hard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o Baptize.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Prieſt, being asked what Saint was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Patron of his Church, <hi>His Name</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> anſwered he) <hi>I know not, only I know him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſight.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:49233:30"/>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>At <hi>Nola,</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> the Jeſuits have a College called <hi>d'Arquo,</hi> the Bow; and another in <hi>France,</hi> at a Town of <hi>Anjou,</hi> called <hi>la Fleche,</hi> or the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. On which one wittily compoſed this following Diſtich;
<q>
                     <l>Arcum <hi>Nola</hi> dedit, dedit illis alma Sagittam</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gallia,</hi> quis Funem quem meruere dabit?</l>
                  </q>
In Engliſh thus.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nola</hi> the Bow, and <hi>France</hi> the Shaft did bring,</l>
                  <l>But who ſhall help them to the hempen String?</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>There are Monks, ſaid one, that have a ſtrict Rule, and a large Conſcience. The Outſide of whoſe Monaſteries is all Peace and Religion, whilſt the Devil and War are within.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis ſtrange, ſaid another, that the <hi>Minimes</hi> ſhould eat no Fleſh, and yet ſmell ſo much as they do of a Shoulder of Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Bernardine</hi> Monk having invited a <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictine</hi> to Supper, the firſt deſired the other to ſay Grace, or (as they call it) the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49233:30"/>
                  <hi>Benedicite, Benedictus,</hi> ſays he, <hi>benedicat.</hi> The other, in anſwer to it, made this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, <hi>Bernardus Bernardet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The Thunder fell one day upon the Steeple of the <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Church at <hi>Paris.</hi> Upon which one ſaid, <hi>It was God's great Mercy, he had ſacrificed only their Steeple to his Juſtice; for, had the Thunder faln into the Kitchin, 'tis like they had all periſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentleman, ſeeing the Monks called <hi>Feuillans</hi> building according to the ſeveral Orders of Architecture, asked <hi>why they did not rather build according to their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>X.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A late French Biſhop had no ſooner given up the Ghoſt, but his Room was preſently plundered. A Cordelier, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt, having got the Biſhop's Breviar, ſnatched alſo a rich Crucifix, ſaying, <hi>Crucifixus etiam pro nobis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Monk being ſent from <hi>Angers</hi> to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> to be puniſhed for his lewd Courſe of Life amongſt Women, was brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Judg, who had then two Ladies with him. <hi>'Tis for your ſakes, Ladies,</hi> ſaid the Monk, <hi>that I am now brought to this. Had not you been,</hi> reply'd the Judg, <hi>ſo looſe upon
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49233:31"/>
Ladies, you would not have brought theſe Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters on your ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>In a Book printed at <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> 'tis ſaid, that a <hi>Carmelite</hi> knocking at Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven's Door, St. <hi>Peter</hi> would not let him in, ſaying, <hi>We ſee none here but</hi> Carme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, <hi>When you can make up a Dozen, you ſhall be let in, not before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An Abbot who had a mind to make his Abbey ſecular, told the French King, that he had the worſt Monks in the World, and that they would not ſay the <hi>Exaudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at. If they be ſo bad,</hi> ſaid the King, <hi>I ought not to rely upon their Prayers, and do freely diſpence them with their</hi> Exaudiat.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another, who had four Abbies, three of which he beſtowed upon his Nephews, invited one Day a Friend of his to come and play with him at Picket. <hi>I don't care,</hi> anſwered his Friend, <hi>to play with a Man who diſcarded ſo many Abbeys.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another Abbot, extreamly given to Playing, loſt 2000 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> at leaſt at one ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with a Duke. The Duke preſſed him for the Payment, ſo that the Abbot wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fain to ſell all he had, which fell much ſhort of the Sum. An Interpoſer pray'd
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49233:31"/>
the Duke to forgive the reſt, in Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment whereof the Abbot ſhould make an <hi>Ode</hi> to his Praiſe, but the worſt he could make. <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>when the World ſhall know, that you made ſo great a Preſent for a wretched Piece, they will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude you would have been much more liberal for a good one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis ſaid of Father <hi>Bourdaloue,</hi> that, when he preached at <hi>Rouen,</hi> the Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men left their Shops, the Merchants their Buſineſs, the Lawyers their Clients, and the Phyſicians their Patients, to hear him. But he that preached there the next Year after ſettled Things in ſo a good Poſture, that none of them forſook their Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Such a one might be that Preacher, who ſo tired his Auditory with a Sermon he made upon Bliſs or Happineſs, that one told him after Sermon, <hi>Sir, you forgot one part of Happineſs, happy are they that did not hear your Sermon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another having divided his Text into 22 Heads, one of his Hearers went out of Church in great haſte. And being asked where he went, <hi>To fetch my Night-Cap,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>for I find we ſhall lie here to Night.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:49233:32"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XIX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Preacher, whoſe Sermons no body cared to hear, intreated a Friend of his to come to hear him. But he begged his Excuſe, ſaying, that <hi>he was loth to diſturb him in his Solitude.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another, who had not the luck to pleaſe his Auditors, <hi>He did better laſt Year,</hi> ſaid one. <hi>How can that be?</hi> ſaid another, <hi>for he did not preach at all. In that very Thing he did better,</hi> reply'd the firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another, preaching at <hi>Paris</hi> to a few Hearers, gave occaſion for one to ſay, that <hi>be preached</hi> ſede vacante. Something like unto it is the Saying of one concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Profeſſor, who read his Lectures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, that <hi>he was</hi> Vox clamantis in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerto.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>One ſpeaking of a Preacher, whom he heard at a great diſtance, <hi>He ſpoke</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>with his Hand, and I heard him with my Eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Of two Preachers, one had a Faculty of making a great Noiſe in the Pulpit. Who paſſing his Verdict upon himſelf and the other, <hi>He preaches</hi> (ſays he) <hi>very well, and I very loud.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:49233:32"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Learned Man of the Roman Church comparing the Way of Preaching of the Antient Fathers of the Church with that of our Modern Preachers, ſaid, <hi>The Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers preached with Zeal and Learning,</hi> whereas in our Days we admire moſt a good Memory and a great Stock of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Friar obſerving from the Pulpit a Woman babbling with another, checked her openly for it. Being nettled at it, up ſhe ſtarts, and cries to the Friar again, <hi>Marry, Sir, I beſhrew his Heart that bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles moſt of us two; I did but whiſper a Word with my Neighbour here, and thou haſt bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled there a good large hour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>During the Tumults in <hi>Paris</hi> in 1649, the ſeditious Party were called <hi>Frondeurs,</hi> that is, Slingers. Theſe in 52, put Straw upon their Hats, to diſtinguiſh themſelves from the oppoſite Party, who wore Paper. A Canon, preaching at that time to the <hi>Bernardine</hi> Monks, had the lucky hit to apply theſe Words of <hi>Job</hi> to the Straw-Party, <hi>In ſtipulam verſi ſunt Lapides fundae,</hi> the Sling-ſtones are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into Straw.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:49233:33"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Roman Catholick confeſſing to a Prieſt, that he had drunk very hard af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Abſolution, pulled ſome Money out of his Pocket, to preſent his Confeſſor with. Who refuſed it, ſaying, <hi>You had beſt keep your Money to drink.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another ſo ſtrangely given to Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he could ſcarce ſpeak three Words together without rapping an Oath, confeſſed, that nothing was more frequent with him, than to ſay, <hi>The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil take me.</hi> Whereupon the Confeſſor told him, how wicked and dangerous ſuch an Expreſſion was; and did ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify him, that he broke out into theſe Words, <hi>The Devil take me, if I ſwear any more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXIX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A beautiful young Lady of <hi>Spain</hi> being at Confeſſion, the Prieſt charmed with her Beauty, and deſirous to get her Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, askt her her Name. But the Lady, unwilling to ſatisfy his wanton Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, checked him in theſe few Words, <hi>Father</hi> (ſaid ſhe to him) <hi>my Name is not a Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:49233:33"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Monk, having quitted his Order, made his Addreſs for Relief to <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> The Prince asked him, <hi>Cujus causâ hûc veniſti? Religionis,</hi> ſaid the Monk. His Highneſs asked him again, <hi>Religio, cujus Generis? Faeminini,</hi> reply'd the Monk. <hi>Ergo,</hi> added the Prince, <hi>tu hûc veniſti propter Genus faemininum.</hi> Which was a hint to the Monk, how ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> was, that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of moſt Monks is very much lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſuſpicion, and that their turning Proteſtants do's too often proceed from a looſe Principle, more than a true Senſe of Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:49233:34"/>
               <head>LAWYERS.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>AN eminent Counſellor at Law, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked why he took upon him ſo many bad Cauſes, being ſo good a Lawyer; <hi>I have</hi> (ſays he) <hi>been caſt in ſo many good Cauſes, and got the better in ſo many bad ones, that I am to ſeek which to chuſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lyſias</hi> having given his Plea to his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Party to peruſe, this read it three times, and gave his Thoughts of it in theſe Words. <hi>The firſt time</hi> (ſays he) <hi>I read it, I liked it well; the ſecond time, not ſo well; and the third, not at all. Then,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Lyſias, it will paſs, for the Court will hear it but once.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Counſellor blind of one Eye, plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Bar with his Spectacles on, ſaid, he would produce nothing but what was <hi>ad Rem,</hi> to the Point. <hi>Then,</hi> ſaid the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Party, <hi>you muſt take out one Glaſs of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49233:34"/>
your Spectacles,</hi> which indeed was Inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another ill favoured Counſellor, who had but half a Noſe left, could not read audibly a Writing that was relating to his Plea. One of the Judges, who had a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſized Noſe, called for Spectacles to help him to read. <hi>Sir,</hi> ſaid the Counſellor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nettled at it, <hi>I hope, if I get Spectacles, you will lend me your Noſe to clap 'em on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>One, whoſe way was to read all his Pleas, having done Reading, another ſtood up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. Who was ſo often interrupted by the firſt, that he told him at laſt, <hi>Sir, by your favour, I let you Read a whole hour without Interruption, pray, let me plead qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly one half Hour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An Advocate of <hi>Toulouſe</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Adam,</hi> made the Preſident all his Spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; except one he ventured to make, in <hi>Adam</hi>'s abſence. Which when the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent delivered, he was ſo puzzled with it, that it made one of the Aſſiſtant Judges cry out, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi es Adam?</hi> where art thou <hi>Adam?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Pick-pocket in <hi>France,</hi> being taken in the Fact at a Court of Judicature, was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately brought before the Court, to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49233:35"/>
anſwer the Charge; and, as the way is there, had Counſel allowed him, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Court, for his Defence. Whereupon his Counſel took him aſide, and asked him, if he had pickt any Man's Pocket? 'Tis true enough, ſays he. Hold your tongue, reply'd the Counſel, and follow my Advice. Go thy ways, and make thy Eſcape with full ſpeed. No ſooner ſaid, but done. And, whilſt the Delinquent took his Opportunity, his Counſel came gravely to the Bar again. The Court asked him, what he had to ſay in his Client's Defence. <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> ſays he, <hi>he has freely owned to me the Matter of Fact. But he being under no Guard, and I appointed his Counſel by the Court, I thought the beſt Counſel I could give him was to make his eſcape; upon which he vaniſhed away pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently.</hi> This proved a Subject of Laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and nothing amiſs could be fixt upon the Lawyer.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A ſtudious Man in the Law took upon him to cut a Partridge at Dinner, but could never hit the Joint. <hi>Sir,</hi> ſaid one of the Gueſts, <hi>Were it not better for you to know leſs of the Law, and underſtand Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy better?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:49233:35"/>
               <head>PHYSICIANS.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>TWO Phyſicians being in Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation about a Patient, they ſpoke Latine together, not think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he underſtood it. At laſt one of them talked of a Remedy, which had not been yet experienced, and ſaid unto the other, <hi>Faciamus periculum in animâ vili,</hi> let us try it upon this poor Soul. Which the Patient over-hearing, he got upon his Knees, and ſaid, <hi>Vilem Animam appellas, pro quâ Chriſtus non dedignatus eſt mori?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> uſed to ſay of a multitude of Books, <hi>Onerat diſcentem Turba,</hi> the great Number of them is rather burdenſom, than uſeful. But one may better ſay of Phyſicians, <hi>Onerat Aegrotum Turba,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more pernicious to a ſick Body, than a Crowd of Phyſicians. For com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the ableſt of 'em is the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted, and minded the leaſt of all.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:49233:36"/>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercatus,</hi> Phyſician to <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King of <hi>Spain,</hi> was ſo familiar with his Maſter, that acting one day the part of a Surgeon in dreſſing the King's Leg, which had a Bone out of Joint, he told him, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a thouſand Piſtols for this Piece of Service. To which the King made this ingenious Return, <hi>Sume quantum vis, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes Claviculum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A facetious Doctor being ſent for to a Gentleman, who could take no Reſt for a Rhume he had in one of his Eyes, upon Examination of the Matter, <hi>Chear up,</hi> ſays he to his Patient, <hi>your Caſe is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate; in few Days all will be well, if you can but</hi> See <hi>it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:49233:36"/>
               <head>ORATORS, <hi>AND</hi> PHILOSOPHERS.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>WHEN <hi>Plato</hi> withdrew from the Court of <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> who would fain have had a famous Philoſopher for his Flatterer, they parted in ſome Unkindneſs, and <hi>Dionyſius</hi> bad him not to ſpeak ill of him, when he was returned into <hi>Greece. Plato</hi> told him, <hi>he had no leiſure for it;</hi> meaning, that he had better Things to mind, than to take up his Thoughts with, and talk of the Faults of ſo bad a Man, ſo notoriouſly known to all the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>When Men ſpeak ill of thee, <hi>ſaid</hi> Plato, live ſo, as no body may believe them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phocion</hi> was very tart in the Orations he made to the <hi>Athenians;</hi> whereas <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes</hi> uſed a quite contrary Method,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49233:37"/>
and ſoothed them up in his Speeches. <hi>If this People,</hi> ſays <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> to <hi>Phocion, do once break looſe upon thee, thou art undone, and they will ſacrifice thy Life to their Fury. Thou runneſt the ſame hazard,</hi> reply'd <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion</hi> to <hi>Demoſthenes, if ever they come to themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great having ſent rich Preſents to <hi>Phocion,</hi> he refuſed them; and asked his Embaſſadors, to what purpoſe he had ſent them to him? <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>he looks upon you as the moſt worthy Man of</hi> Athens. <hi>Then,</hi> reply'd he, <hi>all I deſire of him is to leave me ſuch as he takes me to be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>It was a pretty Fancy of <hi>Diogenes,</hi> when he perceived a tedious Diſcourſe drawing near to a Concluſion, to expreſs his Joy in theſe Words, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, I ſee Land.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame, being brought before <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon, Philip</hi> called him a Spy. <hi>I am ſo,</hi> anſwered <hi>Diogenes, but it is of thy Ambition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Being baniſhed out of <hi>Sinope,</hi> his Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place, he ridiculed his Judges in theſe Lines he ſent them from <hi>Athens. You
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49233:37"/>
have,</hi> ſays he, <hi>baniſhed me from my Native Place, and I confine you to your Houſes. You dwell at</hi> Sinope, <hi>I at</hi> Athens. <hi>Here I converſe with the beſt Men of</hi> Greece, <hi>whilſt you keep company with the worſt of Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Diogenes,</hi> ſeeing a Company of unskilful Archers, none of which could ſhoot near the Mark, went and ſtood juſt before it. Being warned to ſtand off, he refuſed it, ſaying, <hi>he was in the ſafeſt Place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bias,</hi> the Philoſopher, being in a Ship with a Company of lewd Men that called upon the Gods in the diſtreſs of a Storm, <hi>Hold your Tongues,</hi> ſays he to 'em, <hi>that (if poſſible) the Gods may forget you are here.</hi> Thus he pleaſantly reminded them of their Vices, and the Puniſhment they might expect from the Gods whom they called upon.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>X.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> being askt what he learnt by Philoſophy, <hi>I learnt</hi> (ſays he) <hi>to live well with all the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>How comes it, ſaid <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to <hi>Ariſtippus,</hi> that Philoſophers are often ſeen to court Princes, and no Prince minds Philoſophers? <hi>Becauſe,</hi> anſwered
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49233:38"/>
                  <hi>Ariſtippus, Philoſophers know their Wants, and Princes do not know their own.</hi> By which Anſwer he meant, that, when Philoſophers want Neceſſaries, they know how to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to Princes for a Supply; but when Princes are in want of Vertue, Wiſdom, or good Counſel, they are often ignorant of it, which makes 'em neglect the Means to purchaſe it. The Truth is, our Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher (I mean <hi>Ariſtippus</hi>) was none of thoſe conceited Philoſophers, who aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Riches did no ways contribute to the Happineſs of one's Life, and made it their Buſineſs by a ſhew of Arguments to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Wealth contemptible. But, as he knew the Conveniencies thereof, ſo he could make ſhift without it, and frame himſelf to all ſorts of Conditions.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame Philoſopher making his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to the foreſaid Tyrant, in the behalf of a Friend of his, and being denied what he asked, he threw himſelf at his feet to obtain it, and did then obtain it. He was blamed by ſeveral for making ſuch a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, which they thought below a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher. But he confuted them by this witty Saying, that <hi>Dionyſius had his Ears at his Feet;</hi> Meaning, that he heard none but ſuch as humbled themſelves before him.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:49233:38"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A rich <hi>Athenian</hi> asked him what he would have to inſtruct his Son. Five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Drachms, ſaid <hi>Ariſtippus.</hi> Five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, reply'd the <hi>Athenian,</hi> I could buy a Slave for that Money. <hi>Buy one,</hi> reply'd <hi>Ariſtippus, and ſo thou ſhalt have two,</hi> mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Son by the other. Thus he gave him to underſtand, that his Son would have the Vices of a Slave, if the Father did not beſtow what was convenient up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to bring him up.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Socrates</hi> having ſaluted one who took no notice of it, his Friends were angry at the Man's Incivility. <hi>Why ſhould you be angry,</hi> ſaid <hi>Socrates, at the Man, becauſe he is not as civil as I am?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Timon,</hi> ſo famous for his hatred to the whole Mankind, and therefore called <hi>Miſanthropos,</hi> being invited to Dinner by one who affected to imitate him in his Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, <hi>This is,</hi> ſaid the Man to <hi>Timon, a pleaſant Feaſt. 'Twould be ſo,</hi> reply'd <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, if thou waſt not here.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> was very lucky in his Wipes. To a Senator, who was but a Taylor's Son, he ſaid, <hi>Rem acu tetigiſti.</hi> And to a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49233:39"/>
Lawyer, who was a Cook's Son, <hi>Ego quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que tibi Jure favebo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>To one who reflected upon the Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Birth, he ſaid, <hi>The Nobility of thy Family ends with thee, but the Nobility of mine begins with me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>To another, <hi>Metellus</hi> by name, who asked him what his Father was, he made this return, <hi>'Twould be much more difficult,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to gueſs who was thy Father.</hi> Which ſtruck home, <hi>Metellus</hi> his Mother having a wanton Character.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A late Orator got his Hair cut off, in order to wear a Wig; which did ſo ſtrangely alter his Countenance, that his neareſt Friends could ſcarce know him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Being imploy'd to open a Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, which he did to admiration, a Friend of his told him, after the Conference, <hi>Sir, I knew you again only by your Eloquence.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:49233:39"/>
               <head>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THORS.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>CICERO,</hi> to expreſs what Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage he reaped from reading of good Authors, has theſe Words, <hi>Soleo ſaepe in aliena Caſtra tranſire, non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Profuga, ſed tanquam Explorator.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pura Impuritas</hi> is the Character <hi>Lipſius</hi> gives of <hi>Petronius. Pura,</hi> in reference to the Style; <hi>Impuritas,</hi> meaning the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcene Diſcourſes that are in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An Author making a Syſtem of the World, and having ſpent many whole Days about it, <hi>Remember,</hi> ſays a Friend of his unto him, <hi>that, when God created the World, he reſted the ſeventh Day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſaac Voſſius,</hi> intertaining one Day <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Sorbiere</hi> at Dinner, preſſed him to drink, telling him, that <hi>Sorberius</hi> came <hi>à Sorbendo.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:49233:40"/>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An Author's Houſe being on fire, whilſt he was poring on his Books, he called to his Wife, and bad her look to it. <hi>You know,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I don't concern my ſelf with the Houſhold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>Varillas</hi> his <hi>Hiſtory of Hereſies</hi> came out, his very Friends found many Flaws in it. Which made one of them tell him, between Jeſt and Earneſt, that <hi>he had writ a Book full of Hereſies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> a noted Author amongſt us, eſpecially for his Coſmography, hapned to loſe his Way, going to <hi>Oxford,</hi> in the Foreſt of <hi>Whichwood.</hi> Being then at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by one of his Brother's Men, the Man earneſtly intreated him to lead the Way, till he had brought him paſt the Wood to the open Fields. But the Doctor telling him, he could not tell which Way to lead him, <hi>Strange!</hi> ſaid the Fellow, <hi>that you, who made a Book of the whole World, cannot ſo much as find your Way out of this Wood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The French Book called <hi>Les Origines de la Langue Françoiſe,</hi> and written by <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Menage,</hi> being mentioned to Queen <hi>Chriſtina, Menage</hi> (ſays ſhe) <hi>is a Man,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49233:40"/>
who will not only know whence a Word comes, but whether it goes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>One having writ a Book, in order to publiſh it, ſent it firſt to a competent Judg to peruſe it, and have his Opinion of it. Who having peruſed the ſame, told him his Opinion was, that <hi>he ſhould leave out one Half, and ſuppreſs the other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>X.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another being come to wait on a Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Man in the Winter Seaſon, and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with him by the Fire, pulled a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py out of his Pocket, which he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the Preſs, and begged of him to caſt his Eye upon it. Who having read ſome Pages over, but finding little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in't fit for the Publick, held the Book to the Fire; ſaying, <hi>Sir, if you pleaſe, we may bring it to Light preſently, and you will find this the beſt way to gratify the Publick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentleman telling an Author, that he was reduced to live upon the Muſes Milk; <hi>That cannot be,</hi> reply'd the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, <hi>being the Muſes are Virgins, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without Milk, unleſs you have proſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>In the Year 1665, the French Academy were very buſy in ſettling the Gender of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49233:41"/>
a Comet; ſome being for the Maſculine, and others for the Feminine Gender. At laſt ſtarts up one of their Members, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>To what purpoſe is all this Debate, when the Comet now to be ſeen may eaſily deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Point? 'Tis but looking,</hi> adds he, <hi>under its Tail.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An Author, having found but one Fault of the Printer's in a Book of his finiſhed at the Preſs, was in a quandary, whether he ſhould make it <hi>Errata</hi> or <hi>Erratum.</hi> But a Friend of his told him, <hi>Let me but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe the Book, I warrant you I ſhall find ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fault, and that will make it</hi> Errata.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A French Author, in an Epigram of his againſt a Maker of Anagrams, expreſſes thus the Pains he takes to find Words in Words, <hi>Eviſceratis Verba quaerit in Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Daniel Heinſius</hi> loved Drinking, which diſcompoſed him ſometimes for his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures. After one of his drinking Bouts, ſome unlucky Students paſted up theſe Words over the Door of his Lecture-Room, <hi>Daniel Heinſius non leget hodie, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter heſternam Crapulam.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:49233:41"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>To one ſaying, that <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s Style is Dark, it was anſwered, that <hi>it is like E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bony, full of glorious Darkneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur Vaugelas</hi> having obtained a Penſion from the late French King, by the Mediation of Cardinal <hi>Richelieu,</hi> the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal told him, <hi>I hope, Sir, you will not forget the word</hi> Penſion <hi>in your Dictionary. No, my Lord,</hi> anſwered <hi>Vaugelas, neither will I forget the Word</hi> Gratitude.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A famous Member of the French Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demy, being gone to the Academy, took the Abbot <hi>Furetiere</hi>'s Place, whom he had had no Kindneſs for. Some time after, he ſaid, reflecting upon <hi>Furetiere, Here's a Place, Gentlemen, where I am like to come out with a thouſand Impertinencies. Go on,</hi> anſwered <hi>Furetiere, there's one out already.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:49233:42"/>
               <head>POETS.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PHiloxenes,</hi> a Greek Poet, having been condemned by <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Tyrant to work in the Quarries, for not approving ſome Verſes of his making, the Tyrant releaſed him to ſhew him ſome new Verſes of his. And, as he had a great Ambition to paſs for a good Poet, ſo he did not doubt but the Relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Philoxenes</hi> would induce him to give his Approbation to this his Trial of Skill. But he was much ſurpriſed, when the Poet hearing his new Verſes, cry'd out, <hi>Let me go back again to the Quarry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another Poet, who had often preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Auguſtus</hi> with Verſes to his Praiſe, the Emperor in a jocoſe humour told him one Day, that it was but juſt, he ſhould make him ſome Return for his Verſes, and at the ſame time preſented him with an Epigram he had made. Which being read by the Poet, he preſently pulled a Purſe out of his Pocket, in which were
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49233:42"/>
ſome Pieces of Gold. This he preſented to the Emperor, telling him, that <hi>he wiſhed he had a better Preſent to make him, in Return of his fine Verſes.</hi> Thus he cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly inſinuated to the Emperor, that a Poet ought not to be paid by a Prince in his own Coyn; and <hi>Auguſtus</hi> was ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the Fancy, that the Poet fared much the better for it afterwards.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pontanus</hi> having made an Enigm upon a Hole, in this following Verſe,
<q>
                     <l>Dic mihi quid majus fiat quo pluria demas;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Scriverius</hi> anſwered <hi>extempore,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Pontano demas Carmina, major erit.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>Mary Stuart</hi> was Wife to King <hi>Francis</hi> I, this Verſe was made upon her,
<q>
                     <hi>Jure</hi> Scotos, Gallos <hi>Thalamo, Spe poſſidet</hi> Anglos.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An Italian Poet having offered a Copy of Verſes of his to the Cenſure of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Critick, he made ſuch Corrections and Alterations in it, that it proved quite another Thing. <hi>Tutto ſe nê andato in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matura?</hi> Is all filed away into Duſt? ſaid
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49233:43"/>
the Poet, upon ſight of it. Which is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of <hi>Pliny Junior,</hi> who ſays in one of his Epiſtles, <hi>Ferrum expoliendo non tam ſplendeſcit quàm atteritur,</hi> Iron wears out more than it grows bright, by poliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A French Poet, having made an Ode to the King, apply'd himſelf to <hi>Malherbe,</hi> as a competent Judg, in order to improve it. Who, upon the peruſal of it, told him, it wanted but four Words; which the Poet pray'd him to write down himſelf. <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herbe</hi> taking his Pen writ under the Title <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> ROI, To the King,</hi> theſe four Words, <hi>Pour torcher ſon Cul,</hi> To wipe his Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide. That done, he folded up the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and gave it to the Poet; who, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting no Sham put upon him, returned him a thouſand Thanks for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>One <hi>Quinault,</hi> a Frenchman, having made a Play, which was going to be acted, he explained the Drift of it to a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. <hi>The Scene,</hi> ſays he to him, <hi>is in</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padocia; <hi>and, to be a competent Judg of the Piece, one muſt travel thither, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Genius of the People. You are in the right,</hi> anſwered the Gentleman, who had no great liking unto it, <hi>and my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is, that</hi> Cappadocia <hi>would be the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49233:43"/>
moſt proper Place for that Play to be acted in.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another Poet preſenting the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> with <hi>Moliere</hi>'s Epitaph, the Prince told him, <hi>Would to God it were</hi> Moliere <hi>himſelf with your Epitaph.</hi> Thus that clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted Prince expreſſed in a lively man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the great Reſpect he had for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Poet, and the ſlender Eſteem he had for the living.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bonnefons,</hi> a French Poet, who lived in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> III of <hi>France,</hi> is much admired to this Day for his Love-Poetry; but eſpecially for one piece of it, which begins thus, <hi>Dic, Acus, mihi, quid meae Puellae,</hi> &amp;c. The ſame he concludes, bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Needle to prick his Miſtreſs's Heart, not her Finger; which he do's in theſe three admirable Verſes.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Quantam hinc referes, Superba, Laudem!</l>
                  <l>Hâc te cuſpide vulnerâſſe Pectus,</l>
                  <l>Quod nullis potuit <hi>Cupido</hi> Telis.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>X.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another French Poet of good Fame, being blamed for going always on foot, made theſe <hi>Extempore</hi> Verſes;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49233:44"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Je voi d'illuſtres Cavaliers,</l>
                     <l>Avec Laquais, Caroſſe, &amp; Pages;</l>
                     <l>Mais ils doivent leurs Equipages,</l>
                     <l>Et je ne dois pas mes Souliers.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>This following Epigram was made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Bell-Ringers, as a troubleſom ſort of Men in Society;
<q>
                     <l>Great Perſecutors of the Land,</l>
                     <l>Who to our Quiet are a Check,</l>
                     <l>I wiſh you had about your Neck,</l>
                     <l>The Rope that you hold in your hand.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An Engliſh Poet, having made an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Panegyrick of <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook to make one of King <hi>Charles</hi> II, which fell much ſhort of the other. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ask'd the Reaſon of it, <hi>We Poets,</hi> ſaid he to the King, <hi>have always better luck in Fictions, than Realities.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:49233:44"/>
               <head>PAINTERS, <hi>AND</hi> PICT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RES.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>AN Italian Painter, having drawn S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Picture beſpoken by the Pope, His Holineſs found fault with it, that it was too high-coloured. To which the Painter made this bold Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, that <hi>he had repreſented S.</hi> Peter, <hi>bluſhing at the Lives of his Succeſſors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentleman, ſeeing a very good Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of S. <hi>Bruno,</hi> the Founder of the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſian</hi> Order, and being asked his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of it, <hi>Were not it,</hi> ſays he, <hi>for his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Rule, it would ſpeak.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Ear only</hi> (ſaid one of a good Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture) <hi>and not the Eye, can find that it wants Speech.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:49233:45"/>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentleman obſerving, in a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Piece, Juſtice and Peace kiſſing each other, <hi>Do but mind</hi> (ſays he to a Friend of his that ſtood by) <hi>how they imbrace and kiſs each other; They are doubtleſs upon part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and never will meet again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Picture lookt upon to be the Maſter-piece of the famous <hi>le Brun,</hi> repreſenting <hi>Darius</hi> his Royal Family at the Feet of <hi>Alexander,</hi> ſtood between two Originals, one of <hi>Raphael <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbin,</hi> and the other of <hi>Paul Veroneſe.</hi> Cardinal <hi>Chigi,</hi> a Nephew of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> VII, being asked his Opinion about <hi>le Brun</hi>'s Picture, <hi>'Tis very fine,</hi> ſays he, <hi>but it has two ill Neighbours.</hi> By which Anſwer he ingeniouſly gave the preeminency to the two other Pictures, and gave the French to underſtand that <hi>le Brun</hi>'s Picture (thô never ſo good) was not fit to be expoſed near ſuch Originals.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:49233:45"/>
               <head>SCHOLARS.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>IT was a pat Anſwer, which a Scholar made to Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> who asked him in Latin, how often he had been whipt? His Anſwer was in theſe Words Of <hi>Virgil,</hi>
                  <q>Infandum, Regina, jubes renovare Dolorem.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>No leſs ingenious was that poor Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boy, whoſe Condition the Queen being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of, Her Majeſty bad him make ſome Verſes upon this, <hi>Pauper ubique jacet.</hi> Which he wittily performed thus,
<q>
                     <l>In Thalamis, Regina, tuis hâc Nocte jacerem,</l>
                     <l>Si verum hoc eſſet, Pauper ubique jacet.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Scholar riding on Horſeback, and finding that whatever he ſaid to the Horſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49233:46"/>
in Engliſh could not make him go faſt enough, try'd at laſt what he could do in Latin. <hi>Non ibis, mala Beſtia,</hi> ſays he to his Horſe, <hi>etiam admotis Calcaribus?</hi> That is, Won't you go neither, you dull Animal, thô I ſpur thee never ſo much?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another gone a hunting was forewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be ſilent, leſt he ſhould fright the Game away. He hapned to ſee ſome Rabbets, which made him cry out in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, <hi>Ecce Cuniculi.</hi> The Rabbets hearing his Voice fled, and <hi>he wondred</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>how they ſhould come to underſtand Latin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An Univerſity Scholar being ſo hot in Diſcourſe at the Hall-Table that the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows could hear him, the Dean ſent to him to be quiet, with theſe words, <hi>Vir ſapit qui pauca loquitur.</hi> To which he returned this Anſwer, <hi>Vir loquitur qui pauca ſapit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:49233:46"/>
               <head>WAR, OFFICERS, AND SO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LDIERS.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Great Difference (ſaid one) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Peace and War is this, that <hi>in Times of Peace the Sons bury their Fathers, whereas in Time of War the Fathers bury their Sons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saluſtius</hi> ſays, the Romans warred with the Gauls <hi>pro Salute,</hi> for their Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but with the other Nations <hi>pro Gloria,</hi> to advance their Glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon the leaſt Victory got by <hi>MARC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S ANTONI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> there could hardly be found Beaſts enough for Sacrifices. Which made his Friends tell him once, as they were going to Ingage, <hi>We are undone, if you get the Victory.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:49233:47"/>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>At the Battel of <hi>Newport,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> having the Spaniſh Army be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and the Sea behind him, did thus encourage his Souldiers. <hi>If</hi> (ſays he) <hi>you will live, you muſt either eat the Spaniards before us, or drink the Sea behind us.</hi> They choſe the firſt, and fell upon the Spaniards with ſuch an Appetite, that they got an intire Victory over them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>Darius,</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> ſent Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents to <hi>Epaminondas,</hi> that famous Greek Captain, he ſpoke thus to thoſe who brought them. <hi>If</hi> Darius, ſays he, <hi>be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to keep a good Correſpondence with the</hi> Thebans, <hi>he needs not purchaſe my Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and, if he thinks otherwiſe, tell him (as Potent as he is) that he has not Wealth enough to corrupt me.</hi> A noble and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Anſwer, ſhewing in a lively manner both the greatneſs of his Soul, and the clearneſs of his Underſtanding.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A valiant Commander, being told that the Enemy did far exceed him in Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, undauntedly made this return. <hi>Then</hi> (ſays he) <hi>there will be enough for us to kill, enough to take Priſoners, and enough to run away.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:49233:47"/>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Le Baron des Adrets,</hi> a Ring-leader of the Huguenots Party, having took a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle from the Roman Catholicks, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the Garriſon to leap down from the Top of a Tower belonging to the Caſtle. One of the Souldiers ſtept twice forward to the brink of the Precipice, but frighted with the ſight of it ſtept back every time. The Baron bad him leap without any further delay, and threatned to put him to greater Torments, if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined it the third time. <hi>Sir,</hi> anſwered the Souldier, <hi>if you find the Thing ſo eaſy, do you take (if you pleaſe) four Times to do it in.</hi> Which Fancy the Baron was ſo taken with, that he freely forgave him for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A French Officer asking an Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, when we were forced to quit <hi>France,</hi> what Time he thought we ſhould Return thither? <hi>When</hi> (ſays he) <hi>your Sins are greater than ours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A young Officer, ſpeaking of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchal de <hi>Turenne,</hi> ſaid, that he was a pretty Man. <hi>And you, my Son,</hi> ſaid the Father who ſtood by, <hi>are a pretty Sot, to ſpeak thus of the greateſt General in the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:49233:48"/>
               <p>
                  <label>X.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Souldier, being in the Trenches, was called to Dinner by his Comrades. But he anſwered, <hi>He would eat nothing, till he were ſure of a good Digeſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Braggadochio chanced, upon an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, to run away with full ſpeed. Which made one ask him, what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of his great Courage? <hi>'Tis run down,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to my Heels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>In a Sea-fight betwixt the Venetians and the Turks, a Venetian ran into the Hold, and kept ſnug there till the Fight was over. When he found the ſhooting over, he peeped up, and ſaid, <hi>Siam' preſi, ò a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viam preſo?</hi> Are We, or the Turks, beaten?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:49233:48"/>
               <head>TRADESMEN, <hi>AND</hi> CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NTRYMEN.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>SEveral Tradeſmen had great Sums of Money owing them by a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who put them off from Day to Day. One of them coming too cloſe upon him with a preſſing Language, he gave him a box on the Ear. The Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man went to a Magiſtrate, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of it; who adviſed him to leave his Bills with him, and he would take care to ſee them paid. Some time after, the ſaid Magiſtrate brought the Bills to the Gentleman, and asked him whether the Tradeſman had received any Thing in part? <hi>Yes, Sir,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>he had a good Box on the Ear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Dier being commanded by the Court to hold up his Hand, it being all black, the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49233:49"/>
Judg bad him pull off his Glove. <hi>My Lord,</hi> reply'd the Dier, <hi>You had more need put on your Spectacles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Tradeſman that would never work by Candle-light, was asked the reaſon why? <hi>To ſave Candles,</hi> ſays he; <hi>A Peny ſaved is a Peny got.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>One admiring the Happineſs of Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men uſed to ſay, <hi>I will be a Clergy-man in this World, whatever comes on't in the next.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another ſeeing a Wax-taper covered with <hi>Lewis D'or,</hi> and carried for an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to a Saint, being in a Rapture at the ſight of it, cried out, <hi>How glorious and taking are the Church Ceremonies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A melting Sermon being preached in a Country-Church, all fell a weeping, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a Country-man. Who being ask'd, why he did not weep with the reſt? <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</hi> (ſays he) <hi>I am not of this Pariſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Country-man admiring the ſtately Fabrick of S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Cathedral, asked, <hi>Whether it was made in</hi> England, <hi>or brought from beyond Sea.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:49233:49"/>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another being an Eunuch, was asked by a Gentleman, how he came to have no Beard? The Country-man, obſerving he had a Red one, made him this Return; <hi>Sir,</hi> ſays he, <hi>when God was pleaſed to make the Diſtribution of Beards, I came when there was none left but Red ones to diſtribute; and I choſe rather to be without a Beard, than to have a Red one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>One, finding himſelf Indiſpoſed, went to conſult a Phyſician. Who adviſed him to take a Gliſter at Night, to be let Blood and take a Gliſter the next Day, and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick the Day after. Being returned home, and conſidering that he was to go a Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, he took all at once; and ſo ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, without any prejudice to his Health.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>X.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another being at the point of Death, his Son was ſent to the Prieſt of the Pariſh ſomething late in the Night. The Prieſt was faſt aſleep; and the Country-man, loth to awake him, knockt at his Door as modeſtly as he could. Thus he waited three hours at the Door, before he could ſpeak to the Prieſt, as he owned it to him. Who, after he had blamed him for not
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49233:50"/>
knocking harder, <hi>Friend,</hi> ſays he to him, <hi>to be ſure your Father is dead by this time, 'tis too late for me to go. Don't fear,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the Country-man, <hi>for my Neighbour</hi> Pierrot <hi>promiſed me, that he would keep him in Diſcourſe, till I came back.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Woman, whoſe Husband was gone to the Wars, received Information of her Husband's being ſlain in a Battel. Great was her Moan upon it, which drew her neighbouring Goſſips about her. One of which told her, for her Comfort, <hi>Your Husband</hi> (ſays ſhe) <hi>had ſo great a Love for you, that, had he loſt his Life, as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, you would have had an Account of it from himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:49233:50"/>
               <head>MASTERS, <hi>AND</hi> SERVANTS.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Steward to the late Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> repreſented unto him the Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity he lay under to leſſen his Retinue, and gave him a Liſt of ſeveral Servants that he thought fit to diſmiſs. The Prince having examined it, <hi>'Tis true</hi> (ſays he) <hi>I might make ſhift without them; but did you ask them, if they could make ſhift without me?</hi> Thus, without diſproving his Steward's Argument, he baffled it by a ſtronger Reaſon drawn from his generous Nature, and a Principle of Juſtice, requiring all Maſters to have a due Regard for ſuch as have been their Servants.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:49233:51"/>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A young Prince having learnt all his Exerciſes, and made his Courſe of Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, one of his Servants was asked wherein he was moſt ſkilled? <hi>In Riding the great Horſe,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>for his Horſes never flattered him.</hi> Whereby he ſlily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated, that thoſe who had the Care of his Studies ſtood guilty of Flattery.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Maſter ſpeaking of his Servant, <hi>I command more</hi> (ſays he) <hi>than any Man, for before my Servant obeys me in one thing, I muſt command him ten times over.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A great Newſmonger being one day ſurrounded with People, to hear what News he had, he ſpied out amongſt them a Livery-man, whom he bad go his ways. Upon which he made this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, <hi>'Tis my Maſter</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that ſent me to keep a Place for him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon Execution-Days, it was the Way of a Gentleman to ſend out his Footmen to ſee the Execution, and that he called <hi>ſending them to School.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:49233:51"/>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Man of Quality intertaining at Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſeveral Perſons of his Rank, one of his principal Servants did ſomething that did not pleaſe him; for which he gave him a Check before all the Company in Words to this purpoſe, <hi>You little know</hi> (ſays he) <hi>how to carry your ſelf, as you ought. Sir,</hi> reply'd the Servant, <hi>how ſhould I know better, that never lived from you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentleman being gone to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another, one of his Servants told him, <hi>There was no ſpeaking to his Maſter, he being in a ſecret Rapture with his Lady.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A diligent Lackey, come all in a muck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweat to his Maſter, told him, Sir, I made all the haſte I could. <hi>You need ſay no more,</hi> reply'd his Maſter, <hi>for I ſmell it out very well.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentleman in Company with others ſaid, he knew not an honeſt Man, and ſtrenuouſly maintained his Propoſition, which ſome of the Company took offence at. Whilſt they were hot upon this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, a Servant of the Gentleman, in whoſe Houſe they were, came to tell his Maſter, there was an honeſt Man below who deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49233:52"/>
to ſpeak to him. <hi>An honeſt Man,</hi> ſaid his Maſter, <hi>how do you know that, you Raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal?</hi> (Upon which words he gave him a blow with his Cane) <hi>Do you pretend to be more knowing than that Gentleman, who ſays, he knows not ſo much as one honeſt Man?</hi> The Blow was given, and the Servant cried out amain. But, to quiet him, his Maſter gave him a Crown-piece.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:49233:52"/>
               <head>MARRY'D MEN <hi>AND</hi> WOMEN.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Man lookt upon to be Rich, but very much Indebted, courted a good Fortune, and got her. Some Days before their Marriage, he uſed this Stratagem, to ſmother the Reflexions he expected upon the account of his Debts. Being in the Houſe of his future Mother-in-Law, he walkt one day wrapt up with his Cloak, in a melancholy poſture. Upon ſight whereof, ſhe fearing he was out of Order, asked him ſeveral times, <hi>What was the Matter with him?</hi> To which he anſwered as often, <hi>Nothing.</hi> Soon after he was marry'd, his Mother-in-Law, ſeeing what ſhe little expected, a Crowd of Creditors with him, <hi>Son</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49233:53"/>
ſhe) <hi>you have deceived me. You may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, Madam, if you pleaſe</hi> (reply'd the Son-in-Law) <hi>how often I anſwered</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, <hi>when you asked me, before I marry'd,</hi> What was the Matter with me?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An old rich Counſellor, had only one Daughter, courted by a young, proper, and handſom Gentleman, but ſunk in his Fortune. Who, to raiſe himſelf in the World, made it his Buſineſs to compaſs this Lady, with her Father's Conſent. But the Meanneſs of his Eſtate, and her Father's Covetouſneſs, muſt needs be two great Obſtacles. However he found a way, by his Induſtry, to bring his Deſign about. Having got the Lady's good Will, he goes one Day with a good Fee to her Father, in order to have his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. He told him how the Caſe ſtood with him, but concealed the Party. The Counſellor, pleaſed with the Fee, advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to Marry the Lady privately, and offered to give him a Note under his Hand to a Parſon of his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that ſhould Marry them with all ſpeed and ſecrecy. The Buſineſs was done accordingly, and the young Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were marry'd. Which done, he
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:49233:53"/>
brought his Wife to ask her Father's Bleſſing; Who was not a little ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but pleaſed at laſt with the Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Lady unmarried, who had two Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the elder married to a Duke, and the younger going to be marry'd to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Duke, was not a little vexed to ſee her ſelf, as ſhe ſaid, <hi>between two Stools the Breech on the Ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A vertuous Lady being deſired by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to tell her what Method ſhe took to preſerve her Husband's Affection to her; <hi>I make it</hi> (ſays ſhe) <hi>my Buſineſs to pleaſe him in every Thing, and to bear pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently whatever comes amiſs from him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another, being asked in a ſcornful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner what Portion ſhe had brought to her Husband, <hi>What you never had,</hi> anſwered ſhe, <hi>and that is Chaſtity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Man ſeeing his Wife often whiſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Ear of a Gentleman, deſired to know what it was. <hi>I defy you,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:49233:54"/>
ſhe, <hi>to gueſs, for we ſpeak good Things of you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentleman having got his Wife (a Beauty) convicted of Adultery, ſent her to a Monaſtery, and in her place took a Concubine. Which being diſcourſed of in Company, one ſaid, <hi>If the Gentleman had ſuch a fancy to a Whore, he needed not to have parted with his Wife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Piſistratus</hi> being reſolved upon a ſecond Match, his Children asked him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was for any Diſcontent he had received from them? <hi>Far from that,</hi> reply'd he, <hi>for I am ſo well ſatisfy'd with your Carriage to me, that I am willing to have more Children of ſo good a Temper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentleman being reſolved to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, becauſe forſooth he wanted Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny anights, and had no body to ſpeak to, a Woman was brought unto him in theſe Words, <hi>Sir, here's one that will keep you talking.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>X.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another, Married in the Morning, was ſo little affected with it, that he
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49233:54"/>
forgot it before Night, and was a go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to lie at his old Lodging, had not his Man remembred him of his Spouſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Lady had a Husband very kind and complaiſant to her, but that he never minded the ſublime Pleaſures of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugal Life. She complained of this to her own Relations, and they to him. But they ſpeaking of it only in general Terms, he ſaid, he wondered at his Wife's Diſſatisfaction; ſure he was, that he never denied her any Thing ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired. Upon this, her Relations were fain to come to the Point, and to tell him down-right the Cauſe of her Diſcontent. She is to blame, anſwered her Husband, for ſhe never asked me for that ſhe ſo much wants. And they replying, that thoſe things are uſually granted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out asking, he made this Return, <hi>That Thing</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is little worth, which is not worth asking.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A French Counteſs being married to one whom ſhe had no Love for, they were fain at laſt to part, and live aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. The Counteſs after ſome time
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49233:55"/>
changed her Religion, and being asked the Reaſon of it, <hi>I changed</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>that I may not meet my Husband in the next World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Miniſter, having married a cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his Friends, told them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in Merriment, that, if they could not agree, they ſhould come to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and he would unmarry them. It was not long before Diſſentions aroſe between them, and they went both to the Miniſter, in order to be divorced. Who asked them, which of the two had the greateſt Deſire to leave the other? <hi>For</hi> (ſays he) <hi>I married you, till Death does you part; and, before you can be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I muſt diſpatch one of you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>If Adam, <hi>asked one,</hi> were ſtill living, how could he Marry again, all Women be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come from him in a ſtrait Line?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A marry'd Man, ſuſpected of Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency, met with another who had often jeered him about it. <hi>Sir,</hi> ſays he unto him, <hi>your Jeſt is ſpoiled, my Wife is newly brought to bed. Well,</hi> reply'd the other,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:49233:55"/>
                  <hi>your Wife was never lookt upon to be Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Some Ladies ſpeaking of the great Pains they ſuffered in their Labours, <hi>For my part</hi> (ſaid one) <hi>'tis leſs Trouble to me, than to ſwallow the Yolk of an Egg. Then ſure, Madam,</hi> reply'd one of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, <hi>your Throat is very narrow.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:49233:56"/>
               <head>DYING MEN <hi>AND</hi> WOMEN.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>THE ancient Romans were ſo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, and ſo apt to flatter their Emperors, as to Deify them after their Deceaſe. Which made <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſian,</hi> one of their Emperors, being at the point of Death, expreſs himſelf in theſe Words to his Friends about him, <hi>I find,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that I become a God,</hi> mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he was a dying. Which he ſaid probably, in deriſion to the Roman Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and Flattery.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Man condemned to be hanged at <hi>Caen</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> being come to the Place of Execution, proteſted, that he died Innocent, and ſummoned the Judg
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49233:56"/>
to appear that Day Twelve-month be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God. To which the Judg anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>I ſhall be guilty of Default.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Socrates</hi> going to ſuffer Death, <hi>I am ſorry,</hi> ſaid his Wife to him, <hi>that you ſhould die Innocent. And I,</hi> replied <hi>Socrates, ſhould be very ſorry to die otherwiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Syward,</hi> the Martial Earl of <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland,</hi> finding himſelf a dying, roſe out of his Bed, and put on his Armour, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That <hi>it became not a valiant Man to to die lying, like a Beaſt,</hi> and ſo gave up the Ghoſt. As valiantly both ſpoken and performed, as it was by <hi>Veſpaſian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>N. Heinſius,</hi> Son of <hi>Daniel,</hi> being upon his Death-bed, charged a Friend of his with Compliments from him to the Duke of <hi>Montauſier, Monſieur Bigot,</hi> and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral others.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Popiſh Gentleman being at the point of Death, a Confeſſor was brought unto him. And being told what he was come for, he lookt upon him, and ſaid, <hi>I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49233:57"/>
know you, nor you me;</hi> and ſo bidding him farewel, turned his Face from him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Prieſt having given the Extream Unction to another dying Prieſt, aged 90 Years, <hi>Your Turn will come, Brother,</hi> ſaid the dying Prieſt to him, <hi>Your Turn will come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A dying Gentleman adviſing with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about a Preamble to his Will, he told him of one he knew of. Where the uſual Words, <hi>In the Name of the Father, &amp;c.</hi> were followed by theſe, <hi>I ſhall ſoon have done, having but little to bequeath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>One, dictating his Will to ſome Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, left a great many Legacies, more than his Eſtate could bear, and ſhewed his Diſpoſition to leave Something likewiſe to the ſaid Lawyers. Who, having writ hitherto very quietly, began now it was their Concern to ask the Teſtator out of what theſe Legacies muſt be paid? for upon this, ſay they, doth depend the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity of the Will. <hi>That I know very well,</hi> anſwered the Teſtator, <hi>and that's the Thing which puzzles me moſt of all.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:49233:57"/>
               <p>
                  <label>X.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another, well knowing the Steward's way to make Hay while the Sun ſhines, made this an Article of his Will, <hi>I leave nothing to my Steward, becauſe he has ſerved me Twenty Years.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Impious, rather than Witty or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetious, was that Dean's Will in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> III; who bequeathed his Eſtate to the <hi>King,</hi> his Body to the <hi>Earth,</hi> and his Soul to the <hi>Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>One who had been always Jocoſe in his Life-time, lying upon his Death-bed, his chief Clerk came, and deſired he would leave him a Legacy. Upon which he gave him a Key, and told him that, <hi>in ſuch a Drawer he would find that which would make him drink.</hi> Dying not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Young Man greedily opened the Box, and found in it but two red Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Perſon of Quality, deeply indebted, fell dangerouſly ill. His Confeſſor being ſent for, he begged of God, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his Confeſſor, that he would be
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49233:58"/>
pleaſed to prolong his Life, until he had paid his Debts. The Confeſſor, putting the beſt Conſtruction upon his Words, told him, his Principle was ſo juſt, that he hoped God would hear his Prayer. Whereupon the Perſon of Quality, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to one of his Friends, whiſpered theſe Words in his Ear, <hi>Should God grant my Requeſt, I ſhould be ſure never to die, for I would never pay my Debts.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:49233:58"/>
               <head>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RYINGS.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>UPON one's ſaying, that the Heart of King <hi>Francis</hi> I, was bury'd at <hi>Rambouillet,</hi> another ſaid, <hi>Then he is all there, becauſe he was all Heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>Bedford,</hi> Regent of <hi>France,</hi> was buried in the Cathedral of <hi>Rouen</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> in a fair plain Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument. King <hi>Charles</hi> VIII, of <hi>France,</hi> being adviſed by one of his Courtiers to deface it, as a diſgraceful Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to <hi>France,</hi> he would not hearken unto it, but made this generous Return; <hi>Let him reſt in peace,</hi> ſays he, <hi>now he is dead, whom we feared, while he lived.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:49233:59"/>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentleman having ſent his Wife to be buried four or five hours after ſhe was dead, one came and told him, that ſhe was ſcarce cold yet. <hi>No matter,</hi> ſays he, <hi>do as you are bid, ſhe is dead e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for me.</hi> He was in the right, ſhe being of a great age, when he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried her: So that it was ſaid of him, that, to help him to live, he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted Society with a dead Body.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another being buried by his Order, without a Coffin, in a Capuchin's Habit, a Widow that had loſt her Husband by his means, cried out in the funeral-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, <hi>Murderer, thy Diſguiſe will ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify nothing, God will find thee out for all that.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A poor Country-woman in <hi>Poitou</hi> fell into ſuch a Lethargy, that her Husband and all about her gave her over for dead. To bury her, they wrapt her up only in a ſheet, as is uſual with poor people in thoſe Parts, and ſo carried her to the Place of Burial. But the Bearers paſſing too near a Thorn-buſh, ſhe was prick'd alive again out of her Lethargy.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:49233:59"/>
Fourteen Years after, ſhe died in good earneſt. Her Husband, fearing another Reſurrection, remembred ſtill the Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh, in the way to the Church-yard. So that when her Corps came near it, he carefully cried out ſeveral times, <hi>Take heed of the Thorn-buſh, and come not too near the Hedge.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:49233:60"/>
               <head>EPITAPHS.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>UPON King <hi>HENRY</hi> I. Who being dead, his Heart and Brains were bury'd in <hi>Normandy,</hi> and his Body in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>HENRICI,</hi> cujus celebrat Vox publica Nomen,</l>
                  <l>Hoc pro parte jacent Membra ſepulta Loco.</l>
                  <l>Quem neque viventem capiebat Terra, nec unus</l>
                  <l>Defunctum potuit conſepelire Locus.</l>
                  <l>In tria partitus, ſua Jura quibuſque re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignat</l>
                  <l>Partibus, illuſtrans ſic tria Regna tribus.</l>
                  <l>Spiritui <hi>Coelum,</hi> Cordi Cerebroque dicata eſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Neuſtria,</hi> quod dederat <hi>Anglia</hi> Corpus habet.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:49233:60"/>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another Poet made him this flattering Epitaph;
<q>
                     <l>Rex <hi>HENRICUS</hi> obit, Deus olim, nunc Dolor Orbis;</l>
                     <l>Numina flent Numen deperiiſſe ſuum.</l>
                     <l>Mercurius minor Eloquio, vi Mentis Apollo,</l>
                     <l>Jupiter Imperio, Marſque Vigore gemunt, &amp;c.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>MA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>D</hi> the Empreſs was Daughter to the foreſaid King, Wife to <hi>Henry</hi> IV Emperour, and Mother to King <hi>Henry</hi> II. Happy in her Poet, who in one Diſtich thus expreſſed her Princely Parentage, Match, and Iſſue.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Magna <hi>Ortu,</hi> majorque <hi>Viro,</hi> ſed maxima <hi>Partu,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hîc jacet <hi>HENRICI</hi> Filia, Sponſa, Parens,</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:49233:61"/>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon King <hi>HENRY</hi> II, who by his own Right annexed to the Crown of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> the French Provinces of <hi>Anjou, Maine,</hi> and <hi>Touraine;</hi> by his Wife, <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain;</hi> and by Conqueſt, <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Sufficit hic Tumulus, cui non ſuffecerat Orbis,</l>
                  <l>Res brevis ampla mihi, cui fuit ampla brevis.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon King <hi>RICHARD,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Coeur de Lion,</hi> renowned for his Conqueſt of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus,</hi> and great Exploits in the <hi>Holy Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Hic, RICHARDE, jaces. Sed Mors ſi cederet Armis,</l>
                  <l>Victa timore tui cederet ipſa tuis.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>This Epitaph was alſo made upon him.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Iſtius in Morte perimit Formica Leonem.</l>
                  <l>Proh dolor! in tanti Funere Mundus obit.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:49233:61"/>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Queen <hi>JANE,</hi> who died in Child-birth of King <hi>Edward</hi> VI, and uſed for her Device a Phenix, being her paternal Creſt had this alluding thereunto for her Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph;
<q>
                     <l>Phaenix <hi>Jana</hi> jacet, nato Phaenice, dolendum</l>
                     <l>Saecula Phaenices nulla tuliſſe duos.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The ſaid King <hi>EDWARD,</hi> being ſnatched away by Death in his Youth, had this Diſtich made upon him;
<q>
                     <l>Rex, Regis Natus, Regum Decus, unica Regni</l>
                     <l>Speſque Saluſque ſui, conditur hoc Tumulo.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon the Removal of Queen <hi>ELIZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETH</hi>'s Body from <hi>Richmond</hi> (where ſhe died) by water to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> there were written theſe paſſionate doleful Lines.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>The Queen was brought by Water to <hi>Whitehall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>At every ſtroke the Oars Tears let fall,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:49233:62"/>More clung about the Barge; Fiſh under water</l>
                  <l>Wept out their Eyes of Pearl, and ſwam blind after.</l>
                  <l>I think the Barge-men might with eaſier Thighs</l>
                  <l>Have row'd her thither in her Peoples Eyes;</l>
                  <l>For howſoe'r, thus much my Thoughts have ſcann'd,</l>
                  <l>She'd come by Water, had ſhe come by Land.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>X.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon Prince <hi>HENRY,</hi> eldeſt Son of King <hi>James</hi> I.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Reader, Wonder think it none,</l>
                  <l>Thô I ſpeak, and am a Stone.</l>
                  <l>Here is ſhrin'd celeſtial Duſt,</l>
                  <l>And I keep it but in truſt.</l>
                  <l>Should I not my Treaſure tell,</l>
                  <l>Wonder then you might as well,</l>
                  <l>How this Stone could chuſe but break,</l>
                  <l>If it had not learnt to ſpeak.</l>
                  <l>Hence amaz'd, and ask not me,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe theſe ſacred Aſhes be.</l>
                  <l>Purpoſely it is concealed;</l>
                  <l>For, if that ſhould be revealed,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:49233:62"/>All that read would by and by</l>
                  <l>Melt themſelves to tears, and dy.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>XI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>On Queen <hi>ANN,</hi> the ſaid Prince's Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by King <hi>James.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>March</hi> with his Wind has ſtruck a Cedar tall,</l>
                  <l>And weeping <hi>April</hi> mourns the Cedar's Fall,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>May</hi> intends no Flow'rs her Month ſhall bring,</l>
                  <l>Since ſhe muſt loſe the Flow'r of all the Spring.</l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Marches</hi> Wind has cauſed <hi>April</hi> ſhowers,</l>
                  <l>And yet ſad <hi>May</hi> muſt loſe her Flow'r of Flowers.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>XII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon the great <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> who died Victor in the Field.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Seek not, Reader, here to find</l>
                  <l>Intomb'd the Throne of ſuch a Mind</l>
                  <l>As did the brave <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> fill,</l>
                  <l>Whom neither Time nor Death can kill.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:49233:63"/>Go, and read all <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Acts,</l>
                  <l>The Rage of <hi>Scythian</hi> Cataracts,</l>
                  <l>What <hi>Epire, Greece,</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> has done,</l>
                  <l>What Kingdoms <hi>Goths</hi> &amp; <hi>Vandals</hi> won.</l>
                  <l>Read all the World's heroick Story,</l>
                  <l>It is but half this Hero's Glory.</l>
                  <l>They got their Victories living,</l>
                  <l>But our Hero got this dying.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>XIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>This ſhort one alſo was made upon him.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Upon this Place the great <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> died,</l>
                  <l>While Victory lay weeping by his ſide.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>XIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The following Epitaph was made upon Pope <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> born at <hi>Luca;</hi> who of Biſhop of <hi>Oſtia,</hi> became Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and died at <hi>Verona.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Luca</hi> dedit tibi lucem, <hi>LUCI,</hi> Pontificatum</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oſtia,</hi> Papatum <hi>Roma, Verona</hi> mori.</l>
                  <l>Imò <hi>Verona</hi> dedit tibi verè vivere, <hi>Roma</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Exilium, Curas <hi>Oſtias, Luca</hi> mori.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:49233:63"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Theobald</hi> of <hi>Bloys,</hi> Earl of <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne,</hi> Nephew to our <hi>Henry</hi> I, <hi>Giraldus Cambrenſis</hi> made this.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Ille Comes, Comes ille pius <hi>Theobaldus</hi> eras, quem</l>
                  <l>Gaudet habere Polus, Terra carere dolet.</l>
                  <l>Non Hominem poſſum, non audeo dicere Numen;</l>
                  <l>Mors probat hunc Hominem, Vita fuiſſe Deum.</l>
                  <l>Trans Hominem, citraque Deum; plus hoc, minus illud,</l>
                  <l>Neſcio quis, Neuter, inter <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trumque fuit.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>XVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> and Marſhal of <hi>England,</hi> being buried in the Temple-Church, had this Epitaph made for him.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Sum quem Saturnum ſibi ſenſit <hi>Hibernia,</hi> Solem</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Anglia,</hi> Mercurium <hi>Normannia, Gallia</hi> Martem.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:49233:64"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Something like it was that for <hi>Richard de Clare,</hi> Earl of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> and <hi>Hartford,</hi> who died in 1602.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Hîc Pudor <hi>Hippoliti, Paridis</hi> Gena, Senſus <hi>Ulyſſis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aeneae</hi> Pietas, <hi>Hectoris</hi> Ira jacet.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>XVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Suffolk</hi> and his Brother, Sons of <hi>Charles Brandon,</hi> who died of the Sweating Sickneſs at <hi>Bugden,</hi> were buried together with this.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na Fides vivos conjunxit, Religio una,</l>
                  <l>Ardor &amp; in ſtudiis unus, &amp; unus Amor.</l>
                  <l>Abſtulit hos ſimul una Dies, duo Corpora jungit</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rna, ac Mentes unus Olympus habet.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>XIX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon the firſt <hi>Seven Archbiſhops</hi> of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> here's a joint Epitaph, as it is taken out of <hi>Gervaſius Dorobernenſis.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Septem ſunt Anglis Primates &amp; Protopatres,</l>
                  <l>Septem Rectores, coelo ſeptemque Triones,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:49233:64"/>Septem Ciſternae Vitae, ſeptemque Lucernae,</l>
                  <l>Septem ſunt Stellae, quas haec tenet Area Cellae.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>XX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon <hi>Stigand</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> this bitter Epitaph was made by ſome of his Enemies.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Hîc jacet <hi>Herodes Herode</hi> ferocior, hujus</l>
                  <l>Inquinat Infernum Spiritus, Oſſa Solum.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>XXI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A ſpecial Favourer of <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> (who was ſlain at <hi>Chriſtmaſs,</hi> in <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> at <hi>Canterbury</hi>) made this Epitaph upon him, expreſſing the Cauſe, Time, and Place of his Death.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Pro Chriſti ſponſâ, Chriſti ſub Tempore, Chriſti</l>
                  <l>In Templo, Chriſti verus Amator obit.</l>
                  <l>Quinta Dies natalis erat, Flos Orbis ab Orbe</l>
                  <l>Carpitur, &amp; Fructus incipit eſſe Poli.</l>
                  <l>Quis moritur? Praeſul. Cur? Pro Grege.</l>
                  <l>Qualiter? Enſe.</l>
                  <l>Quando? Natali. Quis Locus? Ara Dei.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:49233:65"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vitalis,</hi> Abbot of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> who died in the Reign of <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, had this Epitaph.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Qui Nomen traxit à Vitâ, Morte vocante,</l>
                  <l>Abbas <hi>Vitalis</hi> tranſiit, hîcque jacet.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>XXIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>One <hi>Peter,</hi> a Religious Man, had this.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Petra capit <hi>Petri</hi> Cineres, Animam Petra Chriſtus,</l>
                  <l>Sic ſibi diviſit utraque Petra <hi>Petrum.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>XXIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon fair <hi>Roſamond,</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> the Second's Concubine, one Mr. <hi>Daniel</hi> made this.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Hâc jacet in Tumbâ Roſa Mundi, non <hi>Roſamunda;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Non redolet, ſed olet, quae redolere ſolet.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:49233:65"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The next was made upon <hi>Jacobus Triul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio,</hi> a reſtleſs Man, always in action while he lived.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Hîc Mortuus Requieſcit Semel,</l>
                  <l>Qui-Vivus Requievit Nunquam.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>XXVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon a Gentleman named <hi>None,</hi> buried at <hi>Wimundham,</hi> who gave nothing to the Religious there, this following Epitaph was made.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Hîc ſitus eſt <hi>Nullus,</hi> quia Nullo Nullior iſte;</l>
                  <l>Et quia <hi>Nullus</hi> erat, de <hi>Nullo</hi> Nîl tibi, Chriſte.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>XXVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>At <hi>Geneva</hi> there's an Epitaph in theſe Words;
<q>
                     <l>VIXI <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T VIVIS,</l>
                     <l>MORIERIS <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M MORT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</l>
                     <l>SIC VITA TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:49233:66"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>One without Name had this Inſcription on his Grave;
<q>
                     <l>VIXI, PECC AVI, PAENIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>I,</l>
                     <l>NAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RAE CESSI.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXIX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Which is as Chriſtian as that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane of the Roman,
<q>Amici, dum vivimus, Vivamus.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another did ſet down for his Epitaph this godly Admonition.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Look Man before thee,</l>
                  <l>how thy Death haſteth;</l>
                  <l>Look Man behind thee,</l>
                  <l>how thy Life waſteth;</l>
                  <l>Look on thy right Side,</l>
                  <l>how Death thee deſireth;</l>
                  <l>Look on thy left ſide,</l>
                  <l>how Sin thee beguileth;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:49233:66"/>Look Man above thee,</l>
                  <l>Joys that ever ſhall laſt;</l>
                  <l>Look Man beneath thee</l>
                  <l>the Pains without reſt.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diego de Valles</hi> made this Inſcription for his Tomb at <hi>Rome;</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Certa Dies nulli eſt, Mors certa, incerta ſequentum</l>
                     <l>Cura; locet Tumulum qui ſapit ante ſibi.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Caius</hi> a Learned Phyſician of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg,</hi> and a Cofounder of <hi>Gonvil</hi> and <hi>Caius</hi> Colledg, has only on his Monument there,
<q>F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>I CAI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Julius Scaliger,</hi> only this;
<q>SCALIGERI Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>OD RELIQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:49233:67"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>And Cardinal <hi>Pool</hi>'s is as ſhort, but more ſavouring of Chriſtian Antiquity. Theſe are the Words,
<q>DEPOSIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M POLI CARDINALIS.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Burbidge,</hi> the Tragedian, had one fit for his Profeſſion;
<q>
                     <hi>EXIT</hi> BURBIDGE.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>And Mr. <hi>Weymark,</hi> a conſtant Walker in <hi>Paul</hi>'s, was as well fitted with this;
<q>DEFESS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M AMB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LANDO.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon Sir <hi>Philip Sidney,</hi> I find this;
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>England</hi> had his Body, for ſhe it fed;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Netherland</hi> his Blood, in her Defence ſhed;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="125" facs="tcp:49233:67"/>The <hi>Heavens</hi> have his Soul,</l>
                     <l>the <hi>Arts</hi> have his Fame;</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Souldier</hi> the Grief,</l>
                     <l>the <hi>World</hi> his good Name.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon a Young Man of great hope, a Student of <hi>Oxford</hi> made this;
<q>
                     <l>Short was thy Life,</l>
                     <l>Yet liveſt thou ever;</l>
                     <l>Death has her due,</l>
                     <l>Yet dieſt thou never.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXIX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon Sir <hi>Francis Vere.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>When <hi>Vere</hi> ſought Death, arm'd with his Sword and Shield,</l>
                  <l>Death was afraid to meet him in the Field;</l>
                  <l>But, when his Weapons he had laid aſide,</l>
                  <l>Death, like a Coward, ſtruck him, and he died.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:49233:68"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XL.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Here is a ſhort one, but without any ſtreſs of Wit, upon an ancient Knight, Sir..... <hi>Jernegan,</hi> buried croſs-legged at <hi>Somerly</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Jeſus Chriſt, both God and Man,</l>
                  <l>Save thy Servant <hi>Jernegan.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>XLI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>This following was made for a bad Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, who was buried in the Night under the Name of <hi>Menalcas,</hi> and that without any Ceremony.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Here lieth <hi>Menalcas,</hi> as dead as a Log;</l>
                  <l>Who lived like a Devil, &amp; died like a Dog.</l>
                  <l>But I miſtake, here he doth not ly,</l>
                  <l>For from this Place he parted by and by;</l>
                  <l>Making from hence his Deſcent into Hell,</l>
                  <l>Without either Book, Candle, or Bell.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>XLII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Pleaſant was the Epitaph made upon an ignorant French Abbot, in theſe words;
<q>
                     <l>Cy gît un ignorant Abbé,</l>
                     <l>Qui ne ſavoit ni A, ni B.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:49233:68"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XLIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A drunken Man, <hi>Elderton</hi> by Name, had this made upon him;
<q>
                     <l>Hîc ſitus eſt ſitiens, atque ebrius <hi>Eldertonus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Quid dico, hîc ſitus eſt? hîc potiùs ſitis eſt.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XLIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon an old Miſer, <hi>Sparges</hi> by Name, this was made;
<q>
                     <l>Here lieth Father <hi>Sparges,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That died to ſave Charges.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XLV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon a capricious Man, this;
<q>
                     <l>Here lieth Willing Wills,</l>
                     <l>With his Head full of Wind-mills.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XLVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon another, who was ever out of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour;
<q>
                     <l>Here lieth he,</l>
                     <l>Who with himſelf could never agree.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:49233:69"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XLVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>On a litigious Man;
<q>
                     <l>Here lies he, who in his Life</l>
                     <l>With every Man had ſome Strife;</l>
                     <l>And now he's dead, and in his Grave,</l>
                     <l>His Bones no quiet Reſt can have.</l>
                     <l>For lay your Ear unto this Stone,</l>
                     <l>And you ſhall hear how every Bone</l>
                     <l>Doth crack and beat againſt each other.</l>
                     <l>Pray for his Soul's Health, gentle Brother.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XLVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>One, who had a Shrew to his Wife, writ upon her this Epitaph;
<q>
                     <l>We lived one and twenty Year,</l>
                     <l>As Man and Wife together;</l>
                     <l>I could not ſtay her longer here,</l>
                     <l>She's gone, I know not whither.</l>
                     <l>But did I know, I do proteſt,</l>
                     <l>(I ſpeak it not to flatter)</l>
                     <l>Of all the Women in the World,</l>
                     <l>I ſwear I'd ne're come at her.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="129" facs="tcp:49233:69"/>Her Body is beſtowed well,</l>
                     <l>This handſom Grave did hide her:</l>
                     <l>And ſure her Soul is not in Hell,</l>
                     <l>The Devil could ne're abide her.</l>
                     <l>But I ſuppoſe ſhe's ſoar'd aloft;</l>
                     <l>For in the late great Thunder,</l>
                     <l>Methought I heard her roaring Voice,</l>
                     <l>Rending the Clouds aſunder.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XLIX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>He was more happy in a Wife, who wrote this Diſtich upon her, after her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe;
<q>
                     <l>Quae pia, quae prudens, quae provida, pulchra fuiſti,</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor in aeternum, Chara <hi>MARIA,</hi> vale.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>L.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon a notorious Liar, baſely extract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet by reaſon of his Name claiming Kindred of a moſt noble Family, this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph was made.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Here lies <hi>M. F.</hi> the Son of a Bearward,</l>
                  <l>Who would needs bear Arms in ſpight of the Herald;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="130" facs="tcp:49233:70"/>Which was a Lion as black as a Jeat-ſtone,</l>
                  <l>With a Sword in his Paws inſtead of a Whet-ſtone.</l>
                  <l>Five Sons had this Liar, 'tis worth the revealing;</l>
                  <l>Two arrant Liars, and three hang'd for Stealing.</l>
                  <l>His Daughters were nine, never free from Sores;</l>
                  <l>Three crooked Apoſtles, and ſix arrant Whores.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <label>LI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon a Dier;
<q>
                     <l>He that died ſo oft in ſport,</l>
                     <l>Died at laſt, no colour for't.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>LII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon a Puritan Lock-ſmith.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>A Zealous Lock-ſmith dy'd of late,</l>
                  <l>And did arrive at Heaven's Gate.</l>
                  <l>He ſtood without, and would not knock,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe he meant to pick the Lock.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:49233:70"/>
               <p>
                  <label>LIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>On a Gold-ſmith that Tipt Stone-Jugs with Silver;
<q>
                     <l>He that did tip Stone-Jugs about the Brim,</l>
                     <l>Met with a black Pot, and the Pot tipt him.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>LIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon a Wreſtler;
<q>
                     <l>Death to this Wreſtler gave a fine Fall,</l>
                     <l>That tript up his Heels, and took no hold at all.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>LV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>On a Butcher that marry'd a Tanner's Daughter;
<q>
                     <l>A fitter Match has never bin,</l>
                     <l>The Fleſh is marry'd to the Skin.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:49233:71"/>
               <p>
                  <label>LVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon <hi>Coſier,</hi> the Cobler;
<q>
                     <l>Come, gentle Reader, gentle Friend,</l>
                     <l>Come, and behold poor <hi>Coſier</hi>'s End.</l>
                     <l>Longer in length his Life had gone,</l>
                     <l>But that he had no Laſt ſo long.</l>
                     <l>O mighty Death! whoſe Art can kill</l>
                     <l>The Man that made Soles at his will.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>LVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>On a Child drowned, catching of an Apple;
<q>Diſce meo malo, poſſe carere Malo.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>LVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon two beautiful Children, Brother and Siſter, who wanted each of them an Eye;
<q>
                     <l>Lumine <hi>Acon</hi> dextro caruit, <hi>Leonilla</hi> ſiniſtro,</l>
                     <l>Et potuit Formâ vincere uterque Deos.</l>
                     <l>Parve Puer, Lumen quod habes concede Sorori;</l>
                     <l>Sic tu caecus AMOR, ſic erit illa VEN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:49233:71"/>
               <p>
                  <label>LIX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon a troubleſom, talkative Woman;
<q>
                     <l>Here at laſt doth ſhe lie in quiet,</l>
                     <l>Who whilſt ſhe lived was ever unquiet.</l>
                     <l>Her Husband prays, if by her Grave you walk,</l>
                     <l>You'd gently tread; for, if waked, ſhe'll talk.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>LX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>I conclude with that Ingenious Epitaph made upon <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife by Count <hi>Emanuel Theſaurus,</hi> in theſe Words.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Quam ſtupes muliebrem ſtatuam,</l>
                  <l>Tanto artificio fictam,</l>
                  <l>Artifice caruit.</l>
                  <l>Genita fuit, &amp; ſine Scalpello ſculpta;</l>
                  <l>Et, quod impenſiùs mirere,</l>
                  <l>Olim ſpirabilis, &amp; loquuta.</l>
                  <l>Brevi, Foemina fuit.</l>
                  <l>Dicerem, eſt;</l>
                  <l>Niſi prodigium videretur,</l>
                  <l>Foeminam eſſe, &amp; tacere.</l>
                  <l>Sola Mortalium, nec Imaginis egens, nec Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchri,</l>
                  <l>Ipſa ſuae ſtupiditatis Imago,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:49233:72"/>In ſemita haeret,</l>
                  <l>Et in ſuâ Statuâ tumulatur.</l>
                  <l>Licet igitur intra Metamorphoſes numerare</l>
                  <l>Foeminam ex verâ fictam;</l>
                  <l>Imò nunc veram, quia fictam;</l>
                  <l>Nam quid in Foeminis videas, niſi fictum?</l>
                  <l>Itaque mentiri ſolita, ſe ipſam mentitur.</l>
                  <l>Mortua Vivam ſimulat, vel Viva Mortuam.</l>
                  <l>Magis mirêre,</l>
                  <l>Quòd inſulſa ſalſum migravit in Lapidem;</l>
                  <l>In ſale mortua, quo viva carebat.</l>
                  <l>Sic ſolent Foeminae, ſapiunt cùm pereunt.</l>
                  <l>Ah! fuge hunc ſalem, ſi ſapis, Viator.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:49233:72"/>
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>I.</label>
               </p>
               <p>AMongſt the Articles exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to King <hi>HENRY</hi> VIII. by the Iriſh againſt the Earl of <hi>Kildare,</hi> the laſt was, <hi>Finally, all</hi> Ireland <hi>cannot rule the Earl. Then the Earl ſhall rule all Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſaid the King, and ſo made him his Deputy.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>II.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Perſon of Quality, travelling through <hi>Spain,</hi> went to ſee the <hi>Eſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial,</hi> that ſtately Monaſtery of Monks of St. <hi>Jerom</hi>'s Order. As he was viewing the Magnificence thereof, the Superiour intertained him with
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:49233:73"/>
the hiſtory of its Foundation; and told him how <hi>Philip</hi> II. of <hi>Spain</hi> had erected it in performance of a Vow made by him when the Battel was fought at S. <hi>Quentin</hi> in <hi>Picardy,</hi> if he ſhould come off Victorious. To which the Travellour reply'd, admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſtill the Vaſtneſs of the Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Sure</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that King was in a great Fright, when he made ſo great a Vow.</hi> The Malice and Wit of which Anſwer conſiſts in that it attributes a good Work to a ridiculous Fear, and that it meaſures the pretended Fear of King <hi>Philip</hi> by the Greatneſs of the Building.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>III.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Monſieur <hi>de Bautru,</hi> being ſent by the French King into <hi>Spain,</hi> went to ſee the famous Library of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Monaſtery; where he found ſo ignorant a Library-Keeper, that he could give no Account of moſt Books therein. Upon his Return to Court,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:49233:73"/>
the King asked him what he thought of it. <hi>'Tis a very fine Library,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered Bautru, <hi>but your Majeſty ſhould give the Keeper of it the Keeping of your Exchequer.</hi> Why ſo? ſaid the King of <hi>Spain. Becauſe,</hi> anſwered the other, <hi>he never Imbezelled what you have Intruſted him with.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>IV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another having choſen an Illiterate Man for his Library-keeper, gave Occaſion for an ingenious Lady to ſay of that Library, That <hi>it was a Seraglio, kept by an Eunuch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>V.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The late Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> being with a Cardinal, his Eminence took care not to be behind hand with him, and got the Precedency. The Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal's Chaplain attended him, who reſpectfully ſtept back to make way for the Duke. But the Duke took
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:49233:74"/>
him by the Arm, and made him go before him. <hi>Go on, Sir,</hi> ſays he to him, loud enough for the Cardinal to hear him, <hi>I always give Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men the Precedency.</hi> Thus confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Cardinal with his Chaplain, he let the Cardinal know, that he reſpected all Churchmen as Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Religion, and that conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Chaplain had as much Right as his Maſter to go before him, that is, no Right at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An Athenian telling a Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, that the Athenians had often repulſed the Lacedemonians from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Athens; Tis more than we can ſay of you,</hi> anſwered the other, Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Athenians had never been ſo bold as to attempt the Taking of <hi>Lacedemon.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:49233:74"/>
               <p>
                  <label>VII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon another Athenian's ſaying, that the Lacedemonians grew Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in foreign Countries, <hi>Tis true,</hi> anſwered a Lacedemonian, <hi>but no body contracts Vices at</hi> Lacedemon.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>VIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Scot,</hi> ſo famous for his Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſitting at Table with a young Gallant, was by way of Jeſt, asked by him, what Difference there was between <hi>Scot</hi> and <hi>Sot.</hi> To which he preſently reply'd <hi>Menſa tantùm,</hi> that is, the Table's breadth; for the other ſat juſt over againſt him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>IX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Papiſt asked a Proteſtant, as 'tis their uſual Way, where his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was before <hi>Luther. In the Bible,</hi> ſays he, <hi>where yours never was.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:49233:75"/>
               <p>
                  <label>X.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A pleaſant Fancy of an Italian, by name <hi>Trivelino.</hi> Who falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep one Day, with his Horſe's Bridle twiſted in his Arm, another came who unbridled his Horſe, and got away. <hi>Trivelino</hi> being awaked, and miſſing his Horſe, began to feel himſelf about, ſaying; <hi>Either I am</hi> Trivelino, <hi>or not; If I am</hi> Trive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lino, <hi>my Horſe is loſt; If not, I got a Bridle, but know not how.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>No leſs pleaſant was the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of two Frenchmen in <hi>Florence.</hi> Who looking for one another in the Piazza of the old Palace, could not meet by reaſon of a Croud occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by a Show. Till the <hi>Agnus</hi> being rung for, all the Italians fell on their Knees, and theſe two Frenchmen only remained in a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:49233:75"/>
Poſture; by which means they found one another.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>One being told, that he was all of a piece; <hi>Ay,</hi> ſays he, <hi>but 'tis a good Piece.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another ſpeaking of one, He ſpeaks (ſays he) admirably well. <hi>Well he may,</hi> ſaid one that ſtood by, <hi>for he does nothing but ſpeak.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An Italian carrying ſomething un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Cloak, a Frenchman asked him what it was. A Dagger, ſaid the Italian. But the Frenchman, finding 'twas a Bottle of Wine, took it, and drank it all up. Then returning the Bottle, <hi>here's the Sheath however,</hi> ſays he to him.</p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:49233:76"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Man, looking upon the Stars, fell into a Ditch. Which gave Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to this Verſe,
<q>Qui fuit Aſtrologus, nunc Geometra fuit.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis ſaid of one who well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred what he had lent, but forgot what he had borrowed, that <hi>he had loſt one half of his Memory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentleman boaſting to another, that he had Killed 300 Men in a Ship, the other, to be even with him, told him, that to ſee a fair Lady who kept cloſe in a Room of his next Neighbour, he had ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured one Day to ſlip down her Chimney. Which appearing fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:49233:76"/>
to the Gentleman who in his Conceit had made ſo great a ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>I let you</hi> (ſays he to him) <hi>Kill no leſs than</hi> 300 <hi>Men at one bout, why ſhould not you let me for once ſlip down a Chimney, to ſee a great Beauty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another, being ſet upon by Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers at five a Clock in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> ſays he to 'em, <hi>you open Shop very early to day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XIX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Wiſe was that ſaying of Dr. <hi>Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calf, You, Young Men, do think us Old Men to be Fools; but we Old Men know you to be ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Audite Adoleſcentes Senem</hi> (ſays an Ancient) <hi>quem ipſi Senes audivere Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcentem;</hi> Young Men, hear an Old
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:49233:77"/>
Man, whom Old Men themſelves vouchſafed to hear in his Youth.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Apuleius,</hi> ſeeing a Cloſet all ſet round with precious Stones, ſaid, <hi>Domus haec diem ſuum ſibi ipſi facit,</hi> this Cloſet has its Light from it ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An old Man, in a Company ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Eye-ſight, ſaid theſe Words; <hi>Since I came to be old, I ſee more than when I was young, for I ſee double.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentleman ſeeing a Nobleman Kneeling at Church without a Cuſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, threw his Muff at his Feet. <hi>What d'ye mean,</hi> ſaid the Nobleman, <hi>to throw a Cat between my Legs?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:49233:77"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another being at Maſs, one in a genteel Garb came to kneel by him, and ſoon after ſtretched forth his Hand as privately as he could to him, for a Charity. <hi>Sir,</hi> ſaid the other, finding what he aimed at, <hi>you prevented me, I was juſt going to do the ſame by you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The Creed being ſung but mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a Popiſh Church, one ſtood up, and ſaid, <hi>'twas all falſe.</hi> And turning to thoſe about him, <hi>Don't think,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>that I renounce to the Chriſtian Faith. 'Tis not the Letter I ſpeak of, but the Muſick.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:49233:78"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Friend of mine going beyond Sea, and deſiring me at parting to take a place in his <hi>Album Amicorum,</hi> I writ down this Greek Verſe of <hi>Homer,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</q>
That is, We muſt make much of a Friend while he is with us, and let him go when he thinks fit.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentlewoman complaining, that ſhe catched Cold, whenever ſhe went abroad to buy Things in the Shops, becauſe they lay open and expoſed to the Air, an Acquaintance of hers adviſed her, <hi>Never to go thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but on Sundays and Holy Days.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:49233:78"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>One ſeeking for a Lodging met with a Friend of his, and asked him whether his Landlord's Houſe was very lightſom, or not? <hi>I have,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered his Friend, <hi>lodged there ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Years; but always went out ſo early, and came home ſo very late, that I could never ſee Day-light in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXIX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Another being forced to find a Citizen's Security, and at a loſs how to get it, offered inſtead of it <hi>a Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and a ſhe Citizen.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:49233:79"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis ſaid of one who never eat at home, and railed at every one, that <hi>he never opened his Mouth, but at the Coſt of others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A dignified Clergyman, having invited ſeveral of his Friends to Dinner upon a Fiſh-day, his Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyor told him, he had been in the Market, and that there was no Fiſh left but one Salmon, which was kept for a Judge. Whereupon his Maſter gave him a Bag of Money, bad him go back and <hi>buy the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and the Judge.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:49233:79"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Two Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> being together, one that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> go without a Stick, as the other could not read without Spectacles, the firſt ſeeing the other take up his Spectacles to read, <hi>Rather</hi> (ſays he to him) <hi>than make uſe of Spectacles, I ſhould chuſe to forbear Reading. And I,</hi> reply'd the other, <hi>rather than go with a Stick, I ſhould forbear going.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Montagne</hi>'s Book of Expences, there was this Article amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; <hi>Item, for my lazy Temper,</hi> 1000 <hi>Livers.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:49233:80"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Man, having dreamt that he was eating of a new-laid Egg, went to an Interpreter of Dreams, to know the Meaning of it. Who told him, the White of the Egg ſignify'd Silver, and the Yolk Gold, ſo that he muſt prepare himſelf for a good Chance. And 'twas not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had a Windfal, which brought him both Silver and Gold. He went to thank the Interpreter, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented him with a piece of Silver. But the Interpreter, who loved the Yolk better than the White of an Egg, did not forget to put him in mind of it. <hi>Nil ne de Vitello?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:49233:80"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Perſon of Quality owed a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman a Thouſand Pounds. Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together in a fair Road, where both their Coaches went a good rate, the firſt looking out of the Coach called to the Gentleman, and begged a thouſand Excuſes. <hi>And I beg,</hi> ſaid the Gentleman preſently, <hi>a thouſand Pounds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>To one asking, why a lean Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is apter than a fat one to Love? this Reaſon was given; <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a lean Perſon's Heart being nearer, for want of Fleſh, is more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily wrought upon.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:49233:81"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>If you ask, why borrowed Books ſeldom return to their Owners? this is the Reaſon one gives for it; <hi>Becauſe 'tis eaſier to keep 'em, than what is in them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentleman riding an unruly Horſe, the Horſe capered and kick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and the Rider, unwilling to yield, whipt and ſpurred him as faſt. One that ſtood by bad him, <hi>have more Wit.</hi> Another to whom the Fact was related, <hi>I know the Story,</hi> ſays he, <hi>but 'twas not to the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he ſpoke, 'twas to the Horſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:49233:81"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XXXIX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>One that had a ſtinking Breath fell a ſinging before Company. <hi>The Words are very good,</hi> ſaid one of the Company, <hi>but the Air is naught.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XL.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Miniſter in <hi>Languedoc</hi> made a Walk of Mulberry-Trees before his Church Door, and every Year made Money of the Leaves thereof for the uſe of Silkworms. After ſome Years he beſtowed the Money up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Reparations of the <hi>Portico,</hi> with this Inſcription upon it, <hi>MORI L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:49233:82"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XLI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt time Dr. <hi>Caſaubon</hi> went into the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> before it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>built, he was told concerning the Hall, that it had ſerved four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years for Diſputations. <hi>Ay, but</hi> (ſays he) <hi>was there ever any De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion made in it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XLII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Upon an Eclipſe of the Sun which hapned ſome Years ſince, a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman went to give a Lady of great Quality a Viſit; who ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, What News abroad? <hi>The Sun</hi> (ſays he) <hi>Madam, plays at bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peep.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:49233:82"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XLIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Gentleman ſpeaking of the Houſes of <hi>Paris</hi> ſaid, <hi>They were ſo very high, that they hindered the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the City.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XLIV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>In the Gallery of <hi>Verſailles</hi> there are long Forms of maſſy Silver, ſo that many Men together can't lift one up. Upon ſight whereof the Embaſſadors of <hi>Siam</hi> ſaid, <hi>it was a very good way to ſecure them from Thieves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XLV.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Cardinal <hi>du Perron</hi> had a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who was an Hermaphrodite. When he was born, the Midwife ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained the Caſe thus to the Mother. <hi>Your Son,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>is a Girl, and your Daughter a Boy.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:49233:83"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XLVI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Few People know the Meaning<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of theſe five Vowels, A, E, I, O, U, thus placed in the Arch of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror's Palace of <hi>Vienna.</hi> Where they were put in (it ſeems) to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify, <hi>Auſtriacorum Eſt Imperare Orbi Univerſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>XLVII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Lacedemonian, being asked by one of the chief of <hi>Athens,</hi> but a wicked Man, who was the beſt Man at <hi>Lacedemon,</hi> made him this ſevere Return, <hi>He is the beſt Man there,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that is leaſt like unto thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:49233:83"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XLVIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>An Italian Prieſt, called <hi>il Piovano Arlotto,</hi> famous for witty Repartees, being come to <hi>Naples,</hi> went to pay his Reſpects to King <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> then reigning. Who being informed, that he kept a Book of the moſt noted Errours of the chief Men of his Time, Sovereign Princes not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, asked <hi>Meſſer Piovano,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no he was in his Book. <hi>I'le ſee,</hi> anſwered <hi>Piovano;</hi> who, by the King's Order, went and fetched the Book. Being returned, he ſhewed the King the Place of the Book he was in, with theſe Words, <hi>Errour committed by</hi> Alphonſo <hi>King of</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>in ſending a</hi> German <hi>belonging to his Court into</hi> Germany <hi>with</hi> 12000 Florins <hi>of Gold, to buy Horſes for His Majeſty.</hi> Upon ſight whereof, the King asked him wherein lay the Errour. <hi>In truſting the</hi> German <hi>with
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:49233:84"/>
ſuch a Sum of Money,</hi> anſwered <hi>Pio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vano.</hi> But, <hi>if he comes back with the Horſes,</hi> repli'd the King, <hi>or brings me my Money again, what then,</hi> Meſſer Piovano? <hi>Then,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I'le put your Name out of my Book, and write the</hi> German <hi>inſtead on't.</hi> Which Anſwer the King was ſo well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with, that he ſent home <hi>Piova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> with Preſents, after he had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained him for ſome time at his Court.</p>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:49233:84"/>
               <p>
                  <label>XLIX.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Monk going to Preach ſome Leagues off, went to Dinner at a poor Country-Prieſt's Houſe, who had neither Bread nor Wine good enough for him. The Monk ſent out to buy better, with ſome other Proviſions. And, as he was ready to ſit at Table, he came out with a fine Service of Silver-gilt enamel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Which ſo dazzled the Prieſt, that he asked the Monk, whether he had made his Vow of Poverty. <hi>Do you queſtion it?</hi> ſaid the Monk. <hi>Then,</hi> reply'd the Prieſt, <hi>You and I could make a good honeſt Monk, for you made the Vow of Poverty, and I obſerve it.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:49233:85"/>
               <p>
                  <label>L.</label>
               </p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Oſſuna,</hi> being Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy of <hi>Naples,</hi> went on a great Holy-day to view the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Galleys, in order to ſet ſome Slaves at Liberty, according to his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege. He asked ſeveral of them, what Crime had brought them to their ſlaviſh Condition. And all pretended to be Innocent but one, who freely owned all his Crimes, and confeſſed that he deſerved a much ſeverer Puniſhment. <hi>Away with this wicked Man,</hi> ſaid the Duke, <hi>leſt he ſhould pervert all thoſe good Men of his Gang.</hi> Thus the Galley-Slave, by his ingenuous Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, got his Liberty; whilſt the reſt were ridiculed, for want of Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity.</p>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:49233:85"/>
               <p>
                  <label>LI.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Grandee of <hi>Spain</hi> being deſirous to have a good Scholar with him to converſe with, a Friend of his preſented him one. Whom he asked preſently, whether he could make Verſes. <hi>You ſhall judge of it, My Lord,</hi> ſaid the Scholar, <hi>by what I have done;</hi> and brought him the next day a great Bundle of Spaniſh Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of all ſorts. Upon ſight where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the Grandee told his Friend, that Man was not fit for him. And his Friend asking the Reaſon of it, <hi>I confeſs,</hi> anſwered the Grandee, <hi>that I count him Ignorant who can make no manner of Verſes, but that Man ſure is a great Fool for having made ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as he ſhewed me.</hi> A pleaſant Satyr againſt all profeſſed Poets, I mean ſuch as make it their whole Buſineſs to make Verſes.</p>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:49233:86"/>
               <p>
                  <label>LII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Two Brothers lodging together, who were very like one another, and had the ſame Name, a Gentleman deſired to ſpeak to one of them. Which of them, ſaid one of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, <hi>The Counſellor,</hi> ſaid the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman; They are both Counſellors, anſwered the Servant. <hi>He that Squints;</hi> They ſquint both. <hi>He that is Married;</hi> That they are both. <hi>He that has a handſom Wife;</hi> They are both handſom. <hi>'Tis then he that is a Cuckold;</hi> By my Troth, Sir, I think they are both Cuckolds. Well then, ſaid the Gentleman, theſe two Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are the moſt like that ever I heard of.</p>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:49233:86"/>
               <p>
                  <label>LIII.</label>
               </p>
               <p>A Princeſs of great Wit came into a Province, where the Ladies came to pay her their Reſpects. Finding lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in their Converſe that deſerved her Attention, and being however willing to keep 'em in Diſcourſe, ſhe asked a young Lady of the Town where ſhe was, how many Children ſhe had. <hi>I have three, Madam,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the young Lady. Not long after, the Princeſs, taken up with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Thoughts, asked her again the ſame Queſtion. To which the young Lady made this ſmart Repartee, <hi>I have not, Madam, been brought to Bed, ſince you firſt asked me the Queſtion, and ſo I have ſtill but three.</hi> Which free and pleaſant Anſwer, as it quickened the Princeſs's Attention, ſo ſhe ever ſince had the greater eſteem and love for the Lady.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
